<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/dataseer-ml/../grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="GROBID" version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" when="2019-11-05T19:44+0000">
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a" type="main">Knowledge, attitude, and practice towards mental illness service provision and associated factors among health extension professionals in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher/>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <licence/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Eftu</forename>
                <surname>Ahmed</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Hailu</forename>
                <surname>Merga</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Fessahaye</forename>
                <surname>Alemseged</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <title level="a" type="main">Knowledge, attitude, and practice towards mental illness service provision and associated factors among health extension professionals in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <imprint>
              <date/>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          <idno type="DOI">10.1186/s13033-019-0261-3</idno>
          <note>Ahmed et al. Int J Ment Health Syst (2019) 13:5 RESEARCH</note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords>
          <term>Mental illness service provision</term>
          <term>Knowledge</term>
          <term>Attitude</term>
          <term>Practice</term>
          <term>UHEPs</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <abstract>
        <div>
          <p>
            <s>Background: Mental, neurological and substance use disorders are highly prevalent in Ethiopia which are known to result in substantial disability.</s>
            <s>Improving the knowledge, attitude and practice of the primary health care workers is important to reduce this problem.</s>
            <s>Hence, this study aimed at assessing knowledge, attitude, and practice towards mental illness service provision and associated factors among urban health extension professionals (UHEPs) of Addis Ababa City Administration.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Methods:</head>
          <p>
            <s>A cross sectional study design was used.</s>
            <s>Data was collected from 455 study participants using structured and pre-tested self-administered questionnaire and analyzed using SPSS version 20 software respectively.</s>
            <s>Multivariate logistic regression analysis was performed to identify variables which have significant association with the outcome variables.</s>
            <s>The level of significant association was determined by adjusted odds ratio (AOR) with 95% confidence interval.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Results:</head>
          <p>
            <s>This study showed that 44.0% of urban health extension professionals (UHEPs) had adequate knowledge, 93.4% did not have positive attitude and 75.2% had good practice towards mental illness.</s>
            <s>Age 30 years and above [adjusted odds ratio (AOR): 95% CI 0.55 (0.34, 0.90)], having diploma educational status [AOR 95% CI 0.49 (0.32, 0.78)], and personal history of mental illness [AOR 95% CI 0.10 (0.01, 0.89)] were found to have a negative association with knowledge.</s>
            <s>Presence of job aid (AOR 95% CI 4.30 (2.59, 7.15)) and having good knowledge (AOR 95% CI 0.52 (0.32, 0.85) were increased the practice of service provision of UHEPs.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Conclusion:</head>
          <p>
            <s>Less than half of UHEPs had adequate knowledge, most had unfavorable attitude and about threefourth of them had good practice.</s>
            <s>Presence of job aid and having good knowledge were increased the UHEPs practice of mental health service provision.</s>
            <s>Hence, providing refresher training to UHEPs and fully implementing the national mental health strategy as well as proper clinical supervision and support to improve behavioral change is vital.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
      </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div subtype="dataseer">
        <p>
          <s>mortality.</s>
          <s cert="0.9902059435844421" id="dataset-1" type="Tabular data">Evidence showed that 14% of the global burden of disease, measured in disability-adjusted life years (DALYs), can be attributed to MNS disorders <ref target="#b1" type="bibr">[2]</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>According to WHO Mental Health Atlas 2014, more than 45% of the world population live in a country where there is less than one psychiatrist for every 100,000 people.</s>
          <s>However, relying solely on specialists to provide services for people affected by mental, neurological and substance use or disorders would prevent millions of people from accessing the services they need <ref target="#b2" type="bibr">[3]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Hence, WHO has proposed the development of community mental health services through integration of mental health into the existing primary health care system and mobilization of community resources <ref target="#b3" type="bibr">[4]</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>In Ethiopia, mental illness is the leading non-communicable disorder in terms of burden.</s>
          <s>According to WHO Country Cooperation Strategy (CCS) 2012-2015, in Ethiopia there is an increasing trend of mental health problems.</s>
          <s>This is due to urbanization affects mental health through the influence of increased stressors and factors such as overcrowded and polluted environment, high levels of violence, and reduced social support.</s>
          <s>In order to overcome this, WHO and the Ethiopian Federal Ministry of Health (FMOH) are currently implementing the WHO Mental Health Hap Action Program (mhGAP) aimed at integrating mental health into PHC through a decentralization process.</s>
          <s>Mental Health Gap Action Program (mhGAP) is WHO program aims at scaling up services for mental, neurological and substance use disorders for countries especially with low and middle income <ref target="#b4" type="bibr">[5]</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>In 2003, FMOH launched a new innovative health care plan, the Health Extension Program (HEP) for accelerated expansion of primary health care coverage.</s>
          <s>The HEP professionals are female diploma graduate nurses trained on the Health Extension Program for 3 months.</s>
          <s>While many urban interventions are similar to the rural program, some key differences from the rural setting include the prevention and control of non-communicable disease, mental health, and violence and injury prevention, as these are expected to affect urban populations more significantly.</s>
          <s>Urban health extension professionals are providing services on mental health promotion and mental illness prevention activities, awareness-raising and anti-stigma campaigns, early detection of mental illness, referral and the ongoing needs of persons with severe mental illness <ref target="#b5" type="bibr">[6]</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>The urban health extension professional provides service to 500 households and, schools and youth centers in the area.</s>
          <s>In order to address their knowledge and attitude gap to integrate the mental health into primary health care, in 2015 Ethiopian Federal Ministry of Health (FMOH) has developed "The 2nd generation mental health training package for health extension workers" training manual.</s>
          <s>To the best knowledge of the researcher, there is a serious shortage of information that helps to explain the knowledge, attitude and practice of mental health service provision in country and also in the study setting.</s>
          <s>Hence, this study aimed to assess the knowledge, attitude, and practice towards mental health service provision and associated factors among urban health extension professionals of Addis Ababa City Administration.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Methods and materials</head>
        <p>
          <s>An institution based cross sectional study was conducted in Addis Ababa City in five selected sub cities (Kolfe Keranio, Arada, Addis Ketema, Yeka, and Bole) from October 2017 to December 2017.</s>
          <s>The city has 3,384,569 people living in it according to the 2007 census with an annual growth rate of 3.8%.</s>
          <s>Currently, according to the annual report of 2015 from the Addis Ababa Regional Health Bureau, there are 6 hospitals and 98 health centers under the City Administration.</s>
          <s>Out of 98 health institutions, 60 health centers and 9 hospitals (including hospitals under the FMOH) are providing mental health service to the population.</s>
          <s>This service is provided by health providers who are trained as per the WHO supported mhGAP program.</s>
          <s>Accordingly, every year these health facilities are providing services to over 6000 peoples <ref target="#b6" type="bibr">[7]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Unlike the rural health extension workers, urban health extension professionals are placed within the woreda (the third-level administrative divisions of Ethiopia) health office.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div subtype="dataseer">
        <head>Population</head>
        <p>
          <s>The source population was all urban health extension professionals who were working in Addis Ababa City Administration.</s>
          <s id="dataset-1" type="Tabular Data:Subject Data Table">Whereas, the study population was sampled urban health extension professionals who were working in the selected 44 woredas during the time of data collection and were fulfilled the inclusion criteria.</s>
          <s>The Urban Health Extension Professionals on long vacation or maternity leave were excluded from the study.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Sample size determination and sampling procedure</head>
        <p>
          <s>The sample size was calculated by double population proportion formula using Epi-info7.2.</s>
          <s>The following parameters were considered for the calculation: proportion of Nurses who took training and had good knowledge, 59% and proportion of Nurses who took training and did not have knowledge 40.5%, 84% power, AOR 2.1 and 95% confidence interval <ref target="#b7" type="bibr">[8]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Then, after using design effect of <ref target="#b1" type="bibr">[2]</ref> and non-response rate 10%, the final sample size was 506.</s>
          <s>Multi Stage sampling technique was implemented to select the desired sample.</s>
          <s>At the first stage, five sub cities were selected out of ten sub cities using simple random sampling.</s>
          <s>At the 2nd stage, 44 woredas were selected out of the 62 woredas in the selected sub cities using lottery method.</s>
          <s>Woredas selected were also based on availability of sample to satisfy the desired sample size.</s>
          <s>At the 3rd stage, out of the total 658 UHEPs, 506 UHEPs were selected from the sampled woredas.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Measurements Knowledge</head>
        <p>
          <s>In this study knowledge refers to the understanding of mental illness, which includes causes, its symptom (manifestation), treatment, management and risk factor.</s>
          <s>It was assessed by five questions (four of them were multiple response and one was 'yes' , 'no' and 'I don't know' choices).</s>
          <s>Respondents who got all correct response have got a maximum of 20 points, higher points indicate good knowledge.</s>
          <s>Based on total score and distribution, knowledge on mental illness service provision was categorized into inadequate (&lt; 12 scores) and adequate (≥ 12).</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Attitude</head>
        <p>
          <s>In this study attitude encompasses opinion or perceptions, threat, susceptibility and seriousness that the study participants may have towards mental illness and providing service to person with mental illness.</s>
          <s>It was assessed by 12 questions.</s>
          <s>Based on total score and distribution, attitude on mental illness service provision was categorized into unfavorable (&lt; 9 scores) and favorable (≥ 9).</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div subtype="dataseer">
        <head>Practice</head>
        <p>
          <s>In this study it refers to actions based on knowledge and attitude of the participants in providing mental illness service (diagnosis, referral and counseling) to the community.</s>
          <s cert="0.9849584102630615" id="dataset-2" type="Tabular data">It was assessed by seven questions.</s>
          <s>Based on total score and distribution, practice on mental illness service provision was categorized into poor (&lt; 4 scores) and good (≥ 4).</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Job aid</head>
        <p>
          <s>In this study refers to officially distributed materials (broacher, booklet, flipchart) that can support the UHEPs to make a proper diagnosis, provide better counseling at the point of delivery of service.</s>
          <s>It was assessed by if they have job aids or not.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Data collection tools and procedures</head>
        <p>
          <s>Structured and pretested self-administered questionnaire was used as a tool for data collection.</s>
          <s>The data collection tool was developed and adapted after a thorough review of relevant literature <ref target="#b7" type="bibr">[8]</ref>
            <ref target="#b8" type="bibr">[9]</ref>
            <ref target="#b9" type="bibr">[10]</ref>
            <ref target="#b10" type="bibr">[11]</ref>
            <ref target="#b11" type="bibr">[12]</ref> .</s>
          <s>The questioners were grouped into five sections: socio-demographic characteristics, respondent's knowledge regarding mental illness, respondent's attitude towards mental illness, respondent's practice regarding mental illness service provision to the community and factors associated with mental illness service provision.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>To ensure the quality of data the questionnaire was first developed in English and translated into Amharic, local language.</s>
          <s>Then, different individuals fluent in both languages translated the Amharic version back to English to check its consistency.</s>
          <s>Finally, the instrument was administered in Amharic language.</s>
          <s>Data collectors and supervisors were trained for a day on how to introduce study tools to the study participants and check the completeness of each questionnaire.</s>
          <s>Pretest was also conducted on UHEPs similar study participants from kirkos sub cities in Addis Ababa which was not included in the study to check the validity and reliability.</s>
          <s>Based on the feedback from pretest, possible amendments were made on some parts like changing the choices from one to multiple response possibility.</s>
          <s>During data collection the supervisor checked the filled questionnaires on daily bases for further checkup.</s>
          <s>Then, data were checked for the completeness before entry to computer software for analysis.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Data processing and analysis</head>
        <p>
          <s>The collected data was entered using the Epi-data version 3.1 and analyzed using SPSS version 20.0 statistical software package.</s>
          <s>The analyzed data was presented in the form of table, figūre and text using frequency and summary statistics such as mean, standard deviation and percentage.</s>
          <s>Crude and adjusted odds ratio (OR) were calculated to check statistical association between the dependent and independent variables using the bivariate and multivariable analysis.</s>
          <s>All variables of the study were initially tested for association with knowledge, attitude and practice regarding mental health service provision by using the binary logistic regression model.</s>
          <s>Those which showed statistical association (P &lt; 0.25) in bivariate analysis were putted in the multivariable analysis model to check if the association existed after controlling against all the rest of the variables.</s>
          <s>A cut off value of 0.25 is supported by literature <ref target="#b12" type="bibr">[13,</ref>
            <ref target="#b13" type="bibr">14]</ref> .</s>
          <s>All statistical tests were done by assuming 95% confidence interval and statistical significance was considered at P-value less than 0.05.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Results</head>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Socio-demographic characteristics of respondents</head>
        <p>
          <s>Out of 506 sample size calculated, a total of 455 participants participated in the study giving a response rate of 89.9%.</s>
          <s>The mean age of the study participants was 27.9 years, ranged between 20 and 42 years (SD ± 3.94).</s>
          <s>Among the 455 study participants, 206 (45.3%) were never married and the highest proportion of study participants, 324 (71.3%) were Christian orthodox.</s>
          <s>About three-fourth, 74.5%, of the study participants had diploma in terms of their educational status and 85.9% of them were graduated from private institutions.</s>
          <s>Their mean working experience was 3.71 years (SD ± 2.61) which ranges from 1 month to 10 years <ref target="#tab_1" type="table">(Table 1)</ref> .</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Individual factors of urban health extension professionals (UHEPs)</head>
        <p>
          <s>Among the study participants, only 21 (4.6%) had a family history of mental illness while 377 (82.9%), and 57 (12.5%) hadn`t and did not know if there was a history of mental illness within their families respectively.</s>
          <s>From the study participants, 8 (1.8%) had a personal history of mental illness and 340 (74.7%), and 107 (23.5%) did not have and did not know if they had a personal history of mental illness respectively.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Knowledge of UHEPs on mental illness</head>
        <p>
          <s>Among the study participants 200 (44.0%) had adequate knowledge regarding mental illness.</s>
          <s>The four most frequently selected causes of mental illness by the study participants were stress 435 (38.1%), drug/substance abuse 337 (29.5%), weak nerves 142 (12.4%), and brain chemistry 141 (12.3%).</s>
          <s>Being lonely 356 (17.6%), extreme mood changes 340 (16.8%), and suicidal 316 (15.7%) were the response of the study participants for the manifestation of mental illness.</s>
          <s>Two hundred thirtythree (50.8%) participants responded provision of drugs, counseling and referral are the way to manage mental illness <ref target="#tab_2" type="table">(Table 2)</ref> .</s>
          <s>Respondents were asked for the curability of mental illness and majority of study participants 360 (79.1%) responded mental illness as curable and the rest responded as no and I don`t know.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Attitude of UHEPs towards mental illness</head>
        <p>
          <s>More than three-fourth of the UHEPs, 78.5%, did not have a favorable attitude towards mental illness.</s>
          <s>Among study participants 86 (18.9%) strongly agreed and 171 (37.6%) agreed that people with mental illness are dangerous.</s>
          <s>Similarly, thirty-nine (8.6%) participants strongly agreed and 183 (40.2%) agreed with mentally ill people are unpredictable, and 62 (13.6%) were not sure.</s>
          <s>Seventy-six (16.7%) of them strongly agreed and 187 (41.1%) agreed that mentally ill people can lead a normal life.</s>
          <s>There were 195 (42.9%) who agreed, and 231 (50.8%) who strongly agreed that mentally ill people should be confined to facilities for the rest of their life.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Majority, 284 (62.4%) of the study participants disagreed with the idea of mental illness is a personal weakness; while, only 20 (4.4%) and 64 (14.1%) strongly agreed and agreed respectively.</s>
          <s>Also, 261 (57.4%) disagreed with mental illness counseling should be left for specialists.</s>
          <s>One-fifth, 20%, of the study participants strongly agreed and 174 (38.2%) agreed on medication is effective to treat mental illness <ref target="#tab_3" type="table">(Tables 3 and 4</ref> ).</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Reinforcing and enabling factors for mental illness service provision</head>
        <p>
          <s>Among 455 study participants, only 62 (13.6%) were trained during the 3 months training of their being urban health extension professional; while the majority, 311 (68.4%) didn't know whether they have been trained on mental illness during this time.</s>
          <s>Almost all, 433 (95.2%) of the study participants were not provided in-service training on mental illness since they have started working as urban health extension.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Almost half of the study participants, 226 (49.7%) had job aids that support the provision of mental illness services.</s>
          <s>About three-fourth (74.7%) of the respondents claimed that they got supportive supervision, whereas 281 (61.8%) received one to two supportive supervision visits per month <ref target="#tab_6" type="table">(Table 5)</ref> .</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Practice of mental illness service provision</head>
        <p>
          <s>About 98% of the study participants were providing awareness creation of mental illness to families, individuals, and groups, while 10.8% of them were diagnosing mental illness.</s>
          <s>Most of the study participants 413 (90.8%) were referring (using referral form) clients to further treatment to health centers, general hospitals and hospital that are providing only mental health service.</s>
          <s>Three hundred ninety-two (86.2%) of the study participants were following up on patients they have referred, whereas 388 (85.3%) of the study participants were providing counseling to mentally ill patients <ref target="#tab_7" type="table">(Table 6)</ref> .</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Factors associated with knowledge on mental illness service provision</head>
        <p>
          <s>After bivariate logistic regression analysis; age, religion, educational status, work experience, personal history of mental illness and job aid were candidate variables for multivariate logistic regression analysis with P-value &lt; 0.25.</s>
          <s>Among the socio demographic variables, UHEPs age from 30 to 44 years were 45% less likely to have knowledge when compared to those whose age were 20-29 years [AOR = 95% CI 0.55 (0.34, 0.90)].</s>
          <s>The other socio demographic variables associated with knowledge was their educational status; those Bachelor degree holders were 51% less likely to have adequate knowledge compared to those UHEPs who had diploma [AOR = 95% CI 0.49 (0.32, 0.78)].</s>
          <s>UHEPs who did not have personal history of mental illness were 90% less likely to have adequate knowledge compared to those UHEPs who had personal history [AOR = 95% CI 0.10 (0.01, 0.89)] ( <ref target="#tab_8" type="table">Table 7)</ref> .</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Factors associated with attitude towards mental illness</head>
        <p>
          <s>In a bivariate analysis; in-service training, family history and knowledge of mental illness were candidate variables for multivariate logistic regression analysis with P-value &lt; 0.25.</s>
          <s>Among the variables analyzed for multivariate regression, all the three (in-service training, family history and knowledge) didn't show significant association with attitude.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Factors associated with practice of mental health service provision</head>
        <p>
          <s>In a bivariate analysis; age, educational status, work experience, family history of mental illness, supportive supervision, in-service training and job aid were candidate variables for multivariate logistic regression analysis with (P-value &lt; 0.25).</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Job aid was statistically significant with practice of UHEP towards provision of mental health service.</s>
          <s>Those UHEPs who did not have job-aids were four and half times more likely to have good practice comparing to those who had [AOR = (95% CI 4.30 (2.59, 7.15)].</s>
          <s>Overall knowledge was also associated with practice; those UHEPs who did not have adequate knowledge were 48% less likely to have good practice compared to those UHEPs who had adequate knowledge with [AOR = 95% CI 0.52 (0.32, 0.85)] <ref target="#tab_9" type="table">(Table 8</ref> ).</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Discussion</head>
        <p>
          <s>This study focused on assessing knowledge, attitude, practice and factors associated with the mental illness service provision among urban health extension professionals in Addis Ababa with a view to suggest an appropriate practice.</s>
          <s>According to this study, 44.0% of the study participants had adequate knowledge, when compared to different studies conducted on similar study participants, the result of this study was lower than a study conducted in Addis Ababa, 50% <ref target="#b7" type="bibr">[8]</ref> , Jimma Zone, 89%, <ref target="#b10" type="bibr">[11]</ref> and Chitwan, Nepal, 70% <ref target="#b14" type="bibr">[15]</ref> .</s>
          <s>However, it was higher than the study conducted in Kenya among staffs in general medical facilities which was 34.2% <ref target="#b11" type="bibr">[12]</ref> .</s>
          <s>The possible explanation for this result might be in-service training on mental health is often provided to nurses working in health facilities than urban health extension professionals.</s>
          <s>This reason is also supported by concepts and recommendation from different literature like WHO, which states that adequate training, skills and competencies are required to effectively assess, diagnose, treat, support and refer people with mental disorder <ref target="#b15" type="bibr">[16]</ref> .</s>
          <s>The key recommendation of mhGap in Ethiopia is to provide training for non-mental health professionals to deliver care for people suffering from mental illness <ref target="#b16" type="bibr">[17]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Again, the Ethiopian mental health strategy, to ensure integration of mental health service into primary health care needs and scaling up the service provision basic and in-service training of health professionals at all levels is very important <ref target="#b17" type="bibr">[18]</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Among the study participants involved in this study only 21.5% had a favorable attitude towards mental illness.</s>
          <s>When compared to other studies, it was lower than the study conducted in Addis Ababa, 44.2% <ref target="#b7" type="bibr">[8]</ref> , Chitwan, Nepal, 76.5% <ref target="#b10" type="bibr">[11]</ref> , Nigeria, 43.2% <ref target="#b18" type="bibr">[19]</ref> , and Kenya, 29.4% <ref target="#b11" type="bibr">[12]</ref> .</s>
          <s>The possible explanation for this result might be the relatively low knowledge of urban health extension professionals on the subject matter, low exposure to mental illness service provision and cultural difference.</s>
          <s>According to the Ethiopia mental health strategy, such big percentage of unfavorable attitude among UHEPs who are a grass-root level primary health care cadre and who interact with the community on regular basis can negatively affect the already existing cultural believes (the cause of mental illness is supernatural, sprit possession, and the evil eye) of the community and also affect the outcome expected from the integration and scaling up of the mental health service <ref target="#b17" type="bibr">[18]</ref> .</s>
          <s>WHO mental health policy planning and service development also suggest that, stigma can be reduced through primary health care service provider positive attitude towards mental illness.</s>
          <s>The same literature also indicates the solution to improve primary health care provider`s attitude is training <ref target="#b14" type="bibr">[15]</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>The overall practice of urban health extension professionals related to service provision for mental illness was 75.2%.</s>
          <s>This result was aligned with the finding from the study conducted in Kenya on staffs in the general medical facility, referral of suspected patients to mental health care specialist were reported as 89% <ref target="#b11" type="bibr">[12]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Though the overall practice of mental health service provision was good, only 10.8% were diagnosing mental illness at their level.</s>
          <s>This can be explained from the prospective that low knowledge of UHEPs.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Regarding practicing mental health service provision, about 91% of the study participants were referring the patients with manifestation of mental illness, and larger proportion of UHEPs, 85.3% were providing counseling to the clients and their families.</s>
          <s>Comparing to the low level of attitude among the study participants, this may be due to lack of basic and refresher training on mental health that inevitably missed and leading to miss management of the patients with mental illness which in turn would adversely affect the outcome of the service provision.</s>
          <s>The above statement is also supported by WHO mental health policy planning and service development fact sheet which states that low attitude of primary health care providers can affect the human right protection approach <ref target="#b14" type="bibr">[15]</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Concerning knowledge, UHEPs whose age were from 30 to 44 years were 45% less knowledgeable when compared to those whose age were 20-29 years.</s>
          <s>The finding from Addis Ababa Public Hospital showed nurses whose age were 23-27 years two times more knowledgeable than nurses whose age were greater than 37 years <ref target="#b7" type="bibr">[8]</ref> .</s>
          <s>This result was similar to the study conducted in Kenya that among younger nurses (aged 20-30 years), the proportion of those who were "unaware" related to knowledge in psychiatry were higher than older nurses (aged 40 years and above) <ref target="#b11" type="bibr">[12]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Those UHEPs with an educational status of Bachelor degree were 51% less likely to be knowledgeable than those who had diploma.</s>
          <s>This result was different with the KAP study conducted in Kenya <ref target="#b11" type="bibr">[12]</ref> , in which the proportion of doctors reported knowledgeable about mental disorders was higher than that of nurses.</s>
          <s>Similarly, study conducted in Addis Ababa showed that midwifery nurses were four times more knowledgeable than clinical nurses <ref target="#b7" type="bibr">[8]</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Urban health extension professionals who did not have a personal history of mental illness were 90% less likely to have adequate knowledge compared to those UHEPs who had personal history.</s>
          <s>Possible explanation might be those who already had the history might read further about the issues to have better understanding and manage the problem.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Regarding the practice UHEPs, those who did not have job-aids on mental health service provision were four and half times more likely to have good practice compared to those who had a job aid.</s>
          <s>The possible reason might be those UHEPs who did not have the job aid were using different references that can support their service provision.</s>
          <s>The overall knowledge was also associated with practice; those UHEPs who did not have adequate knowledge were 48% less likely to have good practice compared to those UHEPs who had adequate knowledge.</s>
          <s>The possible reason might be those who had knowledge may provide the service easily.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Limitations</head>
        <p>
          <s>The limitation of this study is the possibility of recall bias that might have been introduced due to some knowledge related questions were difficult to remember because of time.</s>
          <s>To minimize such bias training on probing techniques has been given to the data collectors and supervisors.</s>
          <s>The other limitation of this study is lack of published article on the subject to compare our finding with specifically for the factors associated with the disease.</s>
          <s>Notwithstanding these limitations, we believe that our study has very important findings for strengthening mental health service provision in the study area and areas with similar set up.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Conclusion</head>
        <p>
          <s>The study found out that more than half urban health extension professionals' knowledge towards mental illness appear to be inadequate.</s>
          <s>It is evidence that most of them did not have the opportunity to be exposed to refresher courses related to mental health/illness.</s>
          <s>In addition to this, a significant proportion of UHEPs in this study had poor attitude towards mental illness.</s>
          <s>Despite their poor attitude, they happen to had good practice in providing mental health service around referral, follow up and counseling of mentally ill people in the community.</s>
          <s>Age, educational status and personal history of MI of urban health extension professionals were associated with knowledge and job-aids and knowledge were associated with mental health service provision.</s>
          <s>Therefore, provision of basic and refresher trainings to urban health extension professionals is vital to strengthen evidence based medical diagnosis and prevention, also to fully</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <figure type="table" validated="true" xml:id="tab_1">
        <head>Table 1</head>
        <label>1</label>
        <figDesc>Socio-demographic characteristics of UHEPs in Addis Ababa, 2017</figDesc>
        <table>Variables 
Frequency (n = 455) 
Percentage (%) 

Age group (years) 

20-29 
388 
74.3 

30-44 
117 
25.7 

Mean ± SD 
27.94 ± 3.94 

Marital status 

Ever married 
249 
54.7 

Never married 
206 
45.3 

Religion 

Orthodox 
324 
71.3 

Protestant 
90 
19.8 

Catholic 
8 
1.8 

Muslim 
33 
7.3 

Educational status 

Diploma 
339 
74.5 

Degree 
116 
25.5 

Work experience (years) 
≤ 2.5 
205 
45.1 

2.6-5 
108 
23.7 

5-7.5 
98 
21.5 

7.5 and above 
44 
9.7 

Mean ± SD 
3.71 ± 2.61 

Institution of graduation 

Private 
391 
85.9 

Government 
64 
14.1 

</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="false" xml:id="tab_2">
        <head>Table 2</head>
        <label>2</label>
        <figDesc>Mental illness knowledge among UHEPS in Addis Ababa, 2017</figDesc>
        <table>a Multiple responses 

</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="true" xml:id="tab_3">
        <head>Table 3</head>
        <label>3</label>
        <figDesc>Favorable attitude towards mental illness among UHEPs in Addis Ababa, 2017</figDesc>
        <table>Characteristics 
Frequency (n = 455) 
Percentage (100%) 

Over all attitude 

Favorable 
98 
21.5 

Unfavorable 
357 
78.5 

Medication is effective for treating mentally ill patients 

Strongly agree 
91 
20.0 

Agree 
174 
38.2 

Undecided 
36 
7.9 

Disagree 
140 
30.8 

Strongly disagree 
14 
3.1 

Mentally patient should be able to receive treatment in all health facili-
ties 

Strongly agree 
116 
25.5 

Agree 
143 
31.4 

Undecided 
18 
4.0 

Disagree 
157 
34.5 

Strongly disagree 
21 
4.6 

People with mental illness can lead a normal life 

Strongly agree 
76 
16.7 

Agree 
187 
41.1 

Undecided 
34 
7.5 

Disagree 
130 
28.6 

Strongly disagree 
28 
6.2 

</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="false" xml:id="tab_4">
        <head>Table 4</head>
        <label>4</label>
        <figDesc>Unfavorable attitude towards mental illness among UHEPs in Addis Ababa, 2017Counseling's of mental illness should be left for specialist Counseling is unsuccessful for patient with mental illness Mentally ill patients should be confined to facility to the rest of their life</figDesc>
        <table>Characteristics 
Frequency 
(n = 455) 

Percentage 
(100%) 

People with mental illness are dangerous 

Strongly agree 
86 
18.9 

Agree 
171 
37.6 

Undecided 
44 
9.7 

Disagree 
141 
31.0 

Strongly disagree 
13 
2.9 

Mental illness is sign of personal weakness 

Strongly agree 
20 
4.4 

Agree 
64 
14.1 

Undecided 
32 
7.0 

Disagree 
284 
62.4 

Strongly disagree 
55 
12.1 

Strongly agree 
46 
10.1 

Agree 
81 
17.8 

Undecided 
35 
7.7 

Disagree 
261 
57.4 

Strongly disagree 
32 
7.0 

Strongly agree 
33 
7.3 

Agree 
35 
7.7 

Undecided 
8 
1.8 

Disagree 
278 
61.1 

Strongly disagree 
101 
22.2 

Mentally ill patients are usually violent 

Strongly agree 
64 
14.1 

Agree 
207 
45.5 

Undecided 
45 
9.9 

Disagree 
120 
26.4 

Strongly disagree 
19 
4.2 

Mentally ill patients are usually unpredictable 

Strongly agree 
39 
8.9 

Agree 
183 
40.2 

Undecided 
62 
13.6 

Disagree 
151 
33.2 

Strongly disagree 
20 
4.4 

Mentally ill patients need constant care 

Strongly agree 
285 
62.6 

Agree 
142 
31.2 

Undecided 
3 
0.7 

Disagree 
10 
2.2 

Strongly disagree 
15 
3.3 

Strongly agree 
8 
1.8 

Agree 
8 
1.8 

Undecided 
13 
2.9 

Disagree 
195 
42.9 

Strongly disagree 
231 
50.8 

</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="false" xml:id="tab_5">
        <head>Table 4 (continued)</head>
        <label>4</label>
        <figDesc>If a person become mentally ill once they easily become ill again</figDesc>
        <table>Characteristics 
Frequency 
(n = 455) 

Percentage 
(100%) 

Strongly agree 
22 
4.8 

Agree 
139 
30.5 

Undecided 
49 
10.8 

Disagree 
187 
41.1 

Strongly disagree 
58 
12.7 

</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="false" xml:id="tab_6">
        <head>Table 5</head>
        <label>5</label>
        <figDesc>Reinforcing and enabling factors for mental illness service provision among UHEPs in Addis Ababa, 2017Having job aids to support mental illness service provision</figDesc>
        <table>Characteristics 
Frequency 
(n = 455) 

Percentage 
(100%) 

Training on mental health during the 3 months training 

Yes 
62 
13.6 

No 
82 
18.0 

I don't know 
311 
68.4 

Training on mental health as in-service training 

Yes 
22 
4.8 

No 
433 
95.2 

Yes 
226 
49.7 

No 
229 
50.3 

Supportive supervision on mental illness 

Yes 
340 
74.7 

No 
115 
25.3 

Frequency of supportive supervision (n = 340) 

One to two times per month 
281 
61.8 

Three to four times a month 
59 
13.0 

</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="true" xml:id="tab_7">
        <head>Table 6</head>
        <label>6</label>
        <figDesc>Practice of UHEPs towards mental illness service provision in Addis Ababa, 2017</figDesc>
        <table>Characteristics 
Frequency 
(n = 455) 

Percentage 
(100%) 

Overall practice 

Good 
342 
75.2 

Poor 
113 
24.8 

Provision of awareness creation 

Yes 
445 
97.8 

No 
10 
2.2 

Ever diagnose mental illness 

Yes 
49 
10.8 

No 
406 
89.2 

Refer patient with mental illness 

Yes 
413 
90.8 

No 
42 
9.2 

Provision of counseling to mentally patient people 

Yes 
388 
85.3 

No 
67 
14.7 

</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="false" xml:id="tab_8">
        <head>Table 7</head>
        <label>7</label>
        <figDesc>Factor associated with knowledge of UHEPs towards mental illness service provision in Addis Ababa, 2017COR crude odds ratio, AOR adjusted odds ratio, CI confidence interval * Statistically significant at P value &lt; 0.05</figDesc>
        <table>Characteristics Knowledge 
COR (95% 
CI) 

AOR (95% CI) 

Adequate 
n = 200 

Inadequate 
n = 255 

Age group (years) 

20-29 
137 (68.5) 201 (78.8) 
1.0 
1.0 

30-44 
63 (31.5) 
54 (21.1) 
0.58 (0.38, 
0.89) 

0.55 (0.34, 
0.90)* 

Educational status 

Diploma 
133 (66.5) 206 (80.7) 
1.0 
1.0 

Degree 
67 (33.5) 
49 (19.2) 
0.47 (0.31, 
0.72) 

0.49 (0.32, 
0.78)* 

</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="false" xml:id="tab_9">
        <head>Table 8</head>
        <label>8</label>
        <figDesc>Factors associated with practice of UHEPs towards mental health service provision in Addis Ababa, 2017 * Statistically significant at P value &lt; 0.05 Do you have job aids on MI</figDesc>
        <table>Characteristics Practice 
COR (95% CI) AOR (95% CI) 

Good 
n = 342 

Poor 
n = 113 

Yes 
200 (58.4) 26 (23.0) 1.0 
1.0 

No 
142 (41.5) 87 (76.9) 4.71 (2.89, 
7.67) 

4.32 (2.60, 7.18)* 

Overall knowledge 

Adequate 
163 (47.6) 37 (32.7) 1.0 
1.0 

Inadequate 
179 (52.3) 76 (67.2) 0.53 (0.34, 
0.83) 

0.52 (0.32, 0.85)* 
</table>
      </figure>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="acknowledgement">
        <div>
          <head>Acknowledgements</head>
          <p>
            <s>We would like to thank Jimma University for the provision of the overall support of this research.</s>
            <s>We would also like to thank Addis Ababa City Administration Health Bureau for their Cooperation in providing pertinent information and facilitate the data collection that was instrumental for the study.</s>
            <s>The authors thank supervisors, data collectors and all study participants for their commitment and cooperation in responding to the questionnaire.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Funding</head>
          <p>
            <s>The study was financially supported by Jimma University.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Publisher's Note</head>
          <p>
            <s>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="annex">
        <div>
          <ref type="bibr">13:5</ref>
          <p>
            <s>implement the national mental health strategy and maximize the opportunity of the UHEPs at the community level to improve the burden of mental health problem.</s>
            <s>Moreover, proper clinical supervision and support are also important to improve behavioral change.</s>
            <s>Besides, further study needs to be conducted to explore how jobaids influence the attitude and practice of UHEPs toward mental illness.</s>
            <s>Authors' contributions EA involved in conception, designing methods, analysis, interpretation and drafting of the manuscript.</s>
            <s>FA and HM participated in designing, data analysis, interpretation of the findings and write up of the findings.</s>
            <s>All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</s>
          </p>
          <p>
            <s>Author details 1 UNICEF, Nairobi, Kenya. 2 Department of Epidemiology, Institute of Health, Jimma University, Jimma, Ethiopia.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Competing interests</head>
          <p>
            <s>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Availability of data and materials</head>
          <p>
            <s>All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this article.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Consent to publish</head>
          <p>
            <s>Not applicable.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Ethics approval and consent to participate</head>
          <p>
            <s>The ethical clearance was sought from Jimma University, Institute of Health Ethical review board.</s>
            <s>Then a letter of cooperation was obtained from Addis Ababa City Administration Health Bureau.</s>
            <s>The study participants were briefed about the objective and purpose of the study and their rights of not to participate in the study.</s>
            <s>Accordingly, verbal consent was obtained from each study participant through the attached form at the beginning of each questionnaire for easy understanding and access.</s>
            <s>Moreover, confidentiality of all and partial information that have collected was assured.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="references">
        <listBibl>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b0">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">Mental health care in settings where mental health resources are limited: an easy-reference guidebook for healthcare providers in developed and developing countries</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">P</forename>
                  <surname>Smith</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2014"/>
                <publisher>Archway Publishing</publisher>
                <biblScope from="11" to="14" unit="page"/>
                <pubPlace>Bloomington</pubPlace>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b1">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">World Health Organization. Mental health action gap program (mhGAP): scaling up care for mental, neurological, and substance use disorders. Geneva: World Health Organization</title>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2008"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b2">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">World Health Organization. Mental health atlas. Geneva: World Health Organization</title>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2014"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b3">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">Ethiopia-The health extension program in Ethiopia</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">N</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">W</forename>
                  <surname>Workie</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">Gnv</forename>
                  <surname>Ramana</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <ptr target="http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/356621468032070256/Ethiopia-The-health-extension-program-in-Ethiopia.Accessed21"/>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2013-09"/>
                <publisher>World Bank</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
            <note>Universal health coverage (UNICO) studies series</note>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b4">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">Regional Office for Africa. WHO Country cooperation strategy 2012-2015. Ethiopia: World Health Organization. Regional Office for Africa</title>
              <ptr target="http://www.who.int/iris/handle/10665/136003.Accessed20"/>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2013-09"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
            <note>World Health Organization</note>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b5">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Ethiopia health extension program: an institutionalized community approach for universal health coverage</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">H</forename>
                  <surname>Wang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <surname>Tesfaye</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <surname>Ramana</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">N</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">V</forename>
                  <surname>Gandham</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">T</forename>
                  <surname>Chekagn</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">World Bank Studies</title>
              <imprint>
                <publisher>World Bank</publisher>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b6">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">Bangalore Department of Psychiatry. Knowledge attitude and practice questionnaire of health workers questionnaire: mentally Ill (CAMI) scale (Taylor and Dear</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope from="1981" to="2017" unit="page"/>
              </imprint>
              <respStmt>
                <orgName>National Institute of Mental Health and Neurosciences</orgName>
              </respStmt>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b7">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">attitude and factors associated with mental illness among nurses working in public hospitals</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">G</forename>
                  <surname>Mariam</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <surname>Bedaso</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">G</forename>
                  <surname>Ayano</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Ebrahim</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <surname>Knowledge</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.4172/2471-271X.1000108</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4172/2471-271X.1000108"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J Ment Disord Treat</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">108</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2016"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b8">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">Ethiopian Federal Ministry of Health. The 2nd generation mental health extension program: training package for mental health service</title>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2016"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
            <note>Amharic version</note>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b9">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Assessment of knowledge, attitude and practice of nursing staff towards mental health problem in Jimma Zone Western Ethiopia</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <surname>Deribew</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Tesfaye</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Ethiop J Health Sci</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">199</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2005"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b10">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Knowledge and attitude of nurses regarding mental illness in Chitwan</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">G</forename>
                  <surname>Gurung</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Nepal. J Chitwan Med Coll</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="40" to="43" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2014"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b11">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Knowledge, attitude and practice (KAP) of mental illness among staff in general medical facilities in Kenya: practice and policy implications</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">M</forename>
                  <surname>Ndetei</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">L</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">I</forename>
                  <surname>Khasakhala</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">V</forename>
                  <surname>Mutiso</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">W</forename>
                  <surname>Mbwayo</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.4314/ajpsy.v14i3.6</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.4314/ajpsy.v14i3.6"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Afr J Psychiatry</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="225" to="260" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2011"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b12">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Comparison of stopping rules in forward regression</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">B</forename>
                  <surname>Bendal</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">A</forename>
                  <surname>Afifi</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J Am Stat Assoc</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="46" to="53" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="1977"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b13">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">The impact of confounder selection criteria on effect estimation</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">M</forename>
                  <surname>Mickey</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Greenland</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Am J Epidemiol</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="125" to="162" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="1989"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b14">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">Integrating mental health services into primary health care</title>
              <ptr target="http://www.who.int/mental_health/policy/services/en/index.html"/>
              <imprint/>
            </monogr>
            <note>World Health Organization</note>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b15">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">Integrating mental health into primary care: a global perspective. Geneva: World Family Doctors Caring for People (Wonca)</title>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2010"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
            <note>World Health Organization</note>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b16">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">Federal Ministry of Health, World Health Organization. mhGAP in Ethiopia: proof of concept</title>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2013"/>
                <pubPlace>Geneva, Switzerland</pubPlace>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b17">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia Ministry of Health. National mental health strategy 2012/13-2015/16</title>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2012"/>
                <pubPlace>Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</pubPlace>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b18">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Integrating mental health into primary care in Nigeria: report of a demonstration project using the mental health gap action programme intervention guide</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">O</forename>
                  <surname>Gureje</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Abdulmalik</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">L</forename>
                  <surname>Kola</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">E</forename>
                  <surname>Musa</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">T</forename>
                  <surname>Yasamy</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">K</forename>
                  <surname>Adebayo</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12913-015-0911-3</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-015-0911-3"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">BMC Health Serv Res</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">242</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2015"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
