<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/dataseer-ml/../grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="GROBID" version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" when="2019-11-05T20:16+0000">
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a" type="main">Perspectives of healthcare professionals in Qatar on causes of medication errors: A mixed methods study of safety culture</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher/>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <licence/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Derek</forename>
                <surname>Stewart Id</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff0">
                <orgName type="department">School of Pharmacy and Life Sciences</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">Robert Gordon University</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Aberdeen</settlement>
                  <country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Binny</forename>
                <surname>Thomas</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff0">
                <orgName type="department">School of Pharmacy and Life Sciences</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">Robert Gordon University</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Aberdeen</settlement>
                  <country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
              <affiliation key="aff1">
                <orgName key="instit1" type="institution">Women's Hospital</orgName>
                <orgName key="instit2" type="institution">Hamad Medical Corporation</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Doha</settlement>
                  <region>Qatar</region>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Katie</forename>
                <surname>Maclure</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff0">
                <orgName type="department">School of Pharmacy and Life Sciences</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">Robert Gordon University</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Aberdeen</settlement>
                  <country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Abdulrouf</forename>
                <surname>Pallivalapila</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff1">
                <orgName key="instit1" type="institution">Women's Hospital</orgName>
                <orgName key="instit2" type="institution">Hamad Medical Corporation</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Doha</settlement>
                  <region>Qatar</region>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Wessam</forename>
                <forename type="middle">El</forename>
                <surname>Kassem</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff1">
                <orgName key="instit1" type="institution">Women's Hospital</orgName>
                <orgName key="instit2" type="institution">Hamad Medical Corporation</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Doha</settlement>
                  <region>Qatar</region>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Ahmed</forename>
                <surname>Awaisu</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff2">
                <orgName type="department">College of Pharmacy</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">Qatar University</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Doha</settlement>
                  <region>Qatar</region>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">James</forename>
                <forename type="middle">S</forename>
                <surname>Mclay</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff3">
                <orgName type="department">Institute of Medical Sciences</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">University of Aberdeen</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Aberdeen</settlement>
                  <country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Kerry</forename>
                <surname>Wilbur</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff2">
                <orgName type="department">College of Pharmacy</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">Qatar University</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Doha</settlement>
                  <region>Qatar</region>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Kyle</forename>
                <surname>Wilby</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff2">
                <orgName type="department">College of Pharmacy</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">Qatar University</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Doha</settlement>
                  <region>Qatar</region>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Cristin</forename>
                <surname>Ryan</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff4">
                <orgName type="department">School of Pharmacy</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland</orgName>
                <address>
                  <addrLine>Dublin 2</addrLine>
                  <settlement>Dublin</settlement>
                  <country key="IE">Ireland</country>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Andrea</forename>
                <surname>Dijkstra</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff5">
                <orgName type="institution">Hamad Medical Corporation</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Doha</settlement>
                  <country key="QA">Qatar</country>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Rajvir</forename>
                <surname>Singh</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff5">
                <orgName type="institution">Hamad Medical Corporation</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Doha</settlement>
                  <country key="QA">Qatar</country>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Moza</forename>
                <surname>Al Hail</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff1">
                <orgName key="instit1" type="institution">Women's Hospital</orgName>
                <orgName key="instit2" type="institution">Hamad Medical Corporation</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Doha</settlement>
                  <region>Qatar</region>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <title level="a" type="main">Perspectives of healthcare professionals in Qatar on causes of medication errors: A mixed methods study of safety culture</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <imprint>
              <date/>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          <note>RESEARCH ARTICLE</note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <abstract>
        <div>
          <head>Background</head>
          <p>
            <s>There is a lack of robust, rigorous mixed methods studies of patient safety culture generally and notably those which incorporate behavioural theories of change.</s>
            <s>The study aimed to quantify and explain key aspects of patient safety culture which were of most concern to healthcare professionals in Qatar.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Methods</head>
          <p>
            <s>A sequential explanatory mixed methods design of a cross-sectional survey followed by focus groups in Hamad Medical Corporation, Qatar.</s>
            <s>All doctors, nurses and pharmacists were invited to complete the Hospital Survey on Patient Safety Culture (HSOPS).</s>
            <s>Respondents expressing interest in focus group participation were sampled purposively, and discussions based on survey findings using the Theoretical Domains Framework (TDF) to explain behavioural determinants.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Results</head>
          <p>
            <s>One thousand, six hundred and four questionnaires were received (67.9% nurses, 13.3% doctors, 12.9% pharmacists).</s>
            <s>HSOPS composites with the lowest levels of positive responses were non-punitive response to errors (24.0%</s>
            <s>positive) and staffing (36.2%).</s>
            <s>Specific TDF determinants potentially associated with these composites were social/professional role and identity, emotions, and environmental context and resources.</s>
            <s>Thematic analysis identified issues of doctors relying on pharmacists to correct their errors and being reluctant to alter the prescribing of fellow doctors.</s>
            <s>There was a lack of recognition of nurses' roles and frequent policy non-adherence.</s>
            <s>Stress, workload and lack of staff at key times were perceived to be major contributors to errors.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
      </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div>
        <formula xml:id="formula_0">a1111111111 a1111111111 a1111111111 a1111111111 a1111111111</formula>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>
          <s>Promoting patient safety in healthcare settings is a global challenge, with an estimated one in ten patients being harmed whilst receiving care <ref target="#b0" type="bibr">[1]</ref> .</s>
          <s>In an effort to raise awareness of key concepts and strategies in patient safety, the World Health Organization (WHO) published 'Medication Without Harm, WHO Global Patient Safety Challenge' in March 2017 <ref target="#b1" type="bibr">[2,</ref>
            <ref target="#b2" type="bibr">3]</ref> .</s>
          <s>The challenge calls for action to reduce patient harm which occurs as a result of unsafe medication practices and medication errors <ref target="#b1" type="bibr">[2,</ref>
            <ref target="#b2" type="bibr">3]</ref> .</s>
          <s>The goal is to 'gain worldwide commitment and action to reduce severe, avoidable medication-related harm by 50% in the next five years, specifically by addressing harm resulting from errors or unsafe practices due to weaknesses in health systems'.</s>
          <s>Accumulation of evidence confirms that healthcare professionals often prescribe, dispense and administer medication in ways and circumstances that may increase the risk of patient harm <ref target="#b3" type="bibr">[4]</ref>
            <ref target="#b4" type="bibr">[5]</ref>
            <ref target="#b5" type="bibr">[6]</ref>
            <ref target="#b6" type="bibr">[7]</ref>
            <ref target="#b7" type="bibr">[8]</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Whilst it is noted that the magnitude and nature of medication harm may differ between countries, globally the cost associated with medication errors has been estimated at US$ 42 billion annually <ref target="#b1" type="bibr">[2,</ref>
            <ref target="#b2" type="bibr">3]</ref> .</s>
          <s>The most commonly cited and accepted definition of the term 'medication error' is that of the National Coordinating Council for Medication Error Reporting and Prevention (NCCMERP) in the United States (US), 'any preventable event that may cause or lead to inappropriate medication use or patient harm, while the medication is in the control of the health care professional, patient, or consumer' <ref target="#b8" type="bibr">[9]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Most research literature focuses on errors relating to prescribing, administration and dispensing, with evidence that causation is often complex and multifactorial.</s>
          <s>Systematic reviews have focused on causes of medication errors in different patient populations and settings <ref target="#b9" type="bibr">[10]</ref>
            <ref target="#b10" type="bibr">[11]</ref>
            <ref target="#b11" type="bibr">[12]</ref>
            <ref target="#b12" type="bibr">[13]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Common to all systematic reviews is the relatively poor research methodologies reported in most of the primary literature, a lack of behavioural theory and organisational culture in study design.</s>
          <s>Furthermore, very few studies employed a mixed methods approach to allow quantification and in-depth description and explanation of contributory factors.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Behavioural theories may be used to provide explanation hence providing a robust and rigorous foundation for development of behaviour change interventions.</s>
          <s>The United Kingdom (UK) Medical Research Council (MRC) framework, 'Developing and implementing complex interventions' highlights the importance of considering theory, noting that interventions grounded in theory are more likely to be effective than those developed empirically or pragmatically' <ref target="#b13" type="bibr">[14]</ref> .</s>
          <s>The Theoretical Domains Framework (TDF) is being used increasingly within health-related research to provide insight into influences on behaviour.</s>
          <s>TDF derives from 33 psychological theories and 128 theoretical constructs organised into 14 domains of behavioural determinants, as described in <ref target="#tab_0" type="table">Table 1</ref>
            <ref target="#b14" type="bibr">[15]</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>It is apparent that there is also a need to focus attention on organisational safety culture.</s>
          <s>The 'Study Group on Human Factors' defines organisational safety culture as, 'the product of individual and group values, attitudes, perceptions, competencies, and patterns of behaviour that determine the commitment to, and the style and proficiency of, an organization's health and safety management <ref target="#b15" type="bibr">[16]</ref> .'</s>
          <s>While two systematic reviews have explored interventions to promote safety culture in hospitals in general and acute hospitals specifically, medication safety was not a feature of any primary research <ref target="#b16" type="bibr">[17,</ref>
            <ref target="#b17" type="bibr">18]</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>In an attempt to promote and standardise the measurement of organisational safety culture, the US Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ) and Medical Errors Workgroup of the Quality Interagency Coordination Task Force (QuIC) sponsored the development of the Hospital Survey on Patient Safety Culture (HSOPS) <ref target="#b18" type="bibr">[19]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Items are clustered within 12 composites as presented in <ref target="#tab_1" type="table">Table 2</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Research on medication errors within the Middle East has historically been reported to be of poor quality <ref target="#b19" type="bibr">[20]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Recently, Elmontsri et al. conducted a systematic review to explore the status of patient safety culture in Arab countries based on the findings of the HSOPS <ref target="#b20" type="bibr">[21]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Data from 18 studies across seven countries (excluding Qatar) were included, identifying that composites relating to non-punitive response to error to be infrequently practised in their organisation, that staffing levels were often inadequate and that communication needed to be more open.</s>
          <s>The authors concluded that further research is warranted to provide explanation of these findings and to identify potential interventions to enhance culture and patient safety.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>The aim of the present study was to quantify and explain key aspects of patient safety culture which were of most concern to health professionals in Qatar.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Methods</head>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Study design</head>
        <p>
          <s>A sequential explanatory mixed methods design was employed, with a cross-sectional survey followed by focus groups in samples of questionnaire respondents to provide further depth and explanation of survey findings <ref target="#b21" type="bibr">[22,</ref>
            <ref target="#b22" type="bibr">23]</ref> .</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Setting</head>
        <p>
          <s>The research was conducted within Hamad Medical Corporation (HMC), the main provider of secondary and tertiary healthcare in Qatar.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Cross-sectional survey</head>
        <p>
          <s>The first phase of the research was a cross-sectional survey.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div subtype="dataseer">
        <head>Questionnaire development</head>
        <p>
          <s id="dataset-1" type="Tabular data:Surveys and Questionnaires">The questionnaire was adapted from AHRQ HSOPS with items presented as 5-point Likert type scales; personal and practice demographic items were added.</s>
          <s>The common language of care delivery at HMC is English thus translation into other languages (e.g.</s>
          <s>Arabic) was not required.</s>
          <s>The questionnaire was piloted in a convenience sample of 100 healthcare professionals.</s>
          <s cert="0.9931538105010986" id="dataset-1" type="Tabular data">Test-retest reliability was assessed in pilot respondents by requesting that the questionnaire be completed on a second occasion within an interval of two weeks.</s>
          <s>A high level of test-retest reliability was achieved (p&lt;0.001,</s>
          <s>Cohen's kappa) for all Likert statements.</s>
          <s>The final questionnaire was formatted in Snap 10 Professional (software for web and email questionnaire design, publication, data entry and analysis).</s>
          <s id="dataset-2" type="Tabular data:Subject Data Table">On completion of the questionnaire, respondents were invited to participate in focus groups to discuss responses in more detail.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div subtype="dataseer">
        <head>Recruitment</head>
        <p>
          <s>All doctors, nurses and pharmacists working within HMC were eligible to participate, with no exclusions.</s>
          <s>Three hundred and sixty responses were required to give a margin of error of 5% with 95% confidence intervals <ref target="#b23" type="bibr">[24]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Online participation was encouraged via HMC web alerts and promotional posters; paper-based questionnaires were distributed to all doctors, nurses and pharmacists.</s>
          <s cert="0.8388515710830688" corresp="#dataset-2" id="dataset-2" type="Tabular data:Subject Data Table">Data were collected from mid-January 2016 to mid-April 2016.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div subtype="dataseer">
        <head>Data analysis</head>
        <p>
          <s>Anonymised online submissions were imported into Snap before direct export to SPSS version 21.0 and data cleaned prior to analysis.</s>
          <s>Paper-based questionnaire data were entered manually using the survey link.</s>
          <s>Descriptive statistics were used to describe respondents' demographic and professional characteristics as well as their responses to individual HSOPS safety culture items.</s>
          <s cert="0.975844144821167" id="dataset-3" type="Tabular data">For each composite, a score was determined in line with the recommendations of the AHRQ task force <ref target="#b18" type="bibr">[19]</ref> .</s>
          <s>This involved firstly calculating the percentage of positive responses to each item.</s>
          <s>A positive response may reflect agreement with a positively phrased statement, or may reflect disagreement with a negatively phrased statement.</s>
          <s>Therefore, for positively worded items the percentage of positive responses is the proportion of 'agree' and 'strongly agree' responses to the item, and for negatively worded items the percentage of positive responses is the proportion of disagree and strongly disagree responses to the item.</s>
          <s>Higher percentages (%) therefore reflect more positive responses to HSOPS safety culture items as defined in <ref target="#tab_1" type="table">Table 2</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>The composite score was then expressed as the mean of the positive responses.</s>
          <s>For those composites with overall positive responses of &lt;50%, Chi-square was used to determine any statistically significant associations with demographic variables.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Focus groups</head>
        <p>
          <s>To clarify, explore and explain issues identified in the survey phase, a qualitative approach was employed.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div subtype="dataseer">
        <head>Sampling and recruitment</head>
        <p>
          <s corresp="#dataset-2" type="Tabular data:Subject Data Table">Respondents of the survey who expressed interest in participating in the focus groups were sampled purposively to represent a range of professions, hospitals and number of years of experience.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Data generation</head>
        <p>
          <s>The focus group topic guide was developed following analysis of the questionnaire data, with reference to the TDF <ref target="#b14" type="bibr">[15]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Initial discussions were based around views and experiences on safety culture in relation to causes of medication errors.</s>
          <s>This was followed by targeted discussions around patient cases of errors illustrating errors in prescribing, dispensing and administration in diverse patient groups which led to significant harm.</s>
          <s>TDF domains were used as prompts in relation to potential causes of errors.</s>
          <s>Focus groups were moderated by two experienced qualitative researchers, with informed consent obtained from each participant at the outset.</s>
          <s>Discussions were audio-recorded (with permission), transcribed verbatim and checked for transcribing reliability.</s>
          <s>A clear audit trail was maintained which documented details of data gathering to promote dependability <ref target="#b24" type="bibr">[25]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Sampling and recruitment continued to the point of data saturation, when no new themes emerged from data analysis <ref target="#b25" type="bibr">[26]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Focus groups were conducted between mid-May 2016 and mid-June 2016.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Data analysis</head>
        <p>
          <s>Data analysis followed the Framework Approach, using TDF domains deductively for to generate a coding framework <ref target="#b26" type="bibr">[27]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Two researchers independently read each focus group transcript repeatedly to ensure familiarity, then coded text to one or more TDF domains.</s>
          <s>Any disagreements were resolved by discussion which involved a third researcher if needed.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Ethics</head>
        <p>
          <s>The study received ethical approval from Hamad Medical Corporation, Medical Research Center Qatar, Qatar University Institutional Review Board and Robert Gordon University Research Ethics Sub-Committee.</s>
          <s>Return of the questionnaire was taken as an indication of informed consent; written informed consent was obtained from all focus group participants.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Results</head>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Cross-sectional survey</head>
        <p>
          <s>Respondents' demographics and professional characteristics.</s>
          <s>One thousand, six hundred and four completed questionnaires were received, with most (67.9%) from nurses followed by doctors (13.3%) and pharmacists (12.9%).</s>
          <s>Around three quarters (70.9%) were female, &lt;40 years (76.0%) and almost half (48.1%) with more than 10 years of experience as healthcare professionals.</s>
          <s>Respondents had varying involvement with medicines-related processes as follows: prescribing medicines (15.1%); administering (61.1%); preparation and dispensing (25.9%); and monitoring (42.0%) ( <ref target="#tab_2" type="table">Table 3)</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Patient safety culture items.</s>
          <s>Positive responses to the HSOPS composites and items are given in <ref target="#tab_4" type="table">Table 4</ref> .</s>
          <s>Composites with the lowest levels of mean positive responses were: non-punitive response to errors (24.0%); staffing (36.2%); communication openness (50.5%); handoffs and transitions (53.1%); and supervisor/manager expectations and actions promoting patient safety (56.5%).</s>
          <s>Composites with the highest levels of positive responses were: organisational learning-continuous improvement (85.5%); team working within unit (82.1%); and management support for patient safety (75.4%).</s>
          <s>For the two composites with mean positive responses of &lt;50%, Chi-square was used to determine the associations between percentage positive responses and demographics/professional characteristics.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Non-punitive response to errors-all individual items contributing to this HSOPS composite attracted a low level of positive response, this was particularly the case for items relating to staff concerns over errors being kept in their personnel files (26.2%), and the perception that errors counted against them (14.6%).</s>
          <s>There were highly statistically significant associations with mean composite agreement and gender (females most positive, Χ 2 (1, N = 1547) = 8.23, p&lt;0.005),</s>
          <s>age (older most positive, Χ 2 (4, N = 1555) = 11.62,</s>
          <s>p&lt;0.05)</s>
          <s>and experience as a healthcare professional (the most experienced being most positive, Χ 2 (5, N = 1536) = 18.42, p&lt;0.005).</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Staffing-while all responses attracted a low level of positive response, this was particularly the case for work pressures and speed of work (23.5%).</s>
          <s>There were highly statistically significant associations with mean composite agreement and healthcare professions (doctors most positive and pharmacists least, Χ 2 (2, N = 1494) = 42.06,</s>
          <s>p&lt;0.001),</s>
          <s>age (youngest least and For those ten composites with higher mean agreement, several items had less than half responding positively.</s>
          <s>There were issues around: supervisors/ managers overlooking recurring patient safety problems (31.9% positive); that it was due to chance that serious errors did not occur (36.0%); problems occurring when exchanging information across hospital units (42.9%); staff being able to ask questions if things did not seem right (44.0%); that at particular pressure points supervisors/ managers wanted staff to work faster, even if this required shortcuts to be taken (46.1%); and staff feeling able to question those in positions of authority (46.6%).</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>More detailed data on the responses to individual items within each composite are given in S1 File.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Focus groups</head>
        <p>
          <s>Demographics of participants.</s>
          <s>Two hundred and ninety-five survey respondents (18.4%) expressed interest in participating in focus groups.</s>
          <s>Nine focus groups were conducted (duration 45-60 minutes), at which point data saturation was deemed to have been achieved.</s>
          <s>Fifty-four individuals from different disciplines participated, with just under half (n = 26, 48.1%) being nurses, followed by 18 (33.3%)</s>
          <s>pharmacists and 10 (18.5%) doctors.</s>
          <s>Most were highly experienced with only 11 (20.4%)</s>
          <s>having &lt;5 years of experience.</s>
          <s>During the focus groups, there was wide-ranging discussion across the spectrum of medication errors of prescribing, administration and dispensing.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Behavioural determinants associated with errors.</s>
          <s>Themes and subthemes relating to safety culture identified during focus group discussions are mapped to TDF behavioural determinants, with illustrative quotes provided for each.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>A. Social/professional role and identity (a coherent set of behaviours and displayed personal qualities of an individual in a social or work setting) When an error is made, but is noticed and corrected before affecting the patient, how often is this reported?</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head n="53.5">(agreed)</head>
        <p>
          <s>When an error is made, but has no potential to harm the patient, how often is this reported?</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head n="56.9">(agreed)</head>
        <p>
          <s>When an error is made that could potentially harm the patient but does not, how often is this reported?</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head n="63.8">(agreed)</head>
        <p>
          <s>Overall perceptions of patient safety, overall positive response = 59.1%</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Patient safety is never sacrificed to get more work done 70.6 (agreed)</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head n="1.">Doctors reliance on pharmacists to correct errors.</head>
        <p>
          <s>During discussion, it emerged that there were instances where doctors would rely on pharmacists to correct their prescribing errors and this led to complacency around prescribing,</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>'Yes. Most of the physicians make a medication error and wait for the pharmacist to correct it.' (Focus Group [FG] 5 Pharmacist 4)</head>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head n="2.">Doctors reluctance to alter other doctors' prescribing.</head>
        <p>
          <s>During one focus group, there was concern that doctors were unwilling to alter prescriptions written by other doctors, particularly for doctors from other specialities.</s>
          <s>The doctors considered this to be the responsibility of the original prescriber, even if a prescribing error had been made and initial prescriber was unavailable, 'This will happen when you're in the Ob-Gyn [obstetrics and gynaecology] setup.</s>
          <s>If one physician came from Hamad from other. . .</s>
          <s>from cardiac or other site, if they write any prescription, if you call the Ob-Gyn doctor here, the on duty doctor, she will never agree to change because B. Emotions (a complex reaction pattern, involving experiential, behavioural, and physiological elements, by which the individual attempts to deal with a personally significant matter or event)</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>1. Stress leading to medication errors.</s>
          <s>Stress and high pressure situations were described in all focus groups as influences on medication errors.</s>
          <s>While workload was a common factor leading to stress, patients themselves could also put undue pressure and hence stress of health professionals,</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>' And I think that probably the stresses of the work [lead to errors].' (FG1 Doctor 2)</head>
        <p>
          <s>' And parents are too tense than they are. . .</s>
          <s>even the parents they are too much angry.</s>
          <s>Yeah, they will scold the staff then like that time they will get pressure.'</s>
          <s>(FG7 Nurse 3)</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>C. Environmental Context and Resources</head>
        <p>
          <s>(any circumstance of a person's situation or environment that discourages or encourages the development of skills and abilities, independence, social competence, and adaptive behaviour)</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Much of the discussion centred on aspects of environmental context and resources as key influences leading to medication errors.</s>
          <s>These were discussed by all participants in all focus groups.</s>
          <s>There were several key themes within this domain.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>1. Workload issues leading to medication errors.</s>
          <s>Workload issues were discussed by doctors, nurses and pharmacists.</s>
          <s>Doctors believed one of the reasons for errors to happen was the heavy workload that they had.</s>
          <s>One pharmacist noted that the excessive workload for the doctor can lead to errors occurring and that this workload also put pressure on other health professionals which could compound errors.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>'There are two problems here, a load on the physician that can lead to many mistakes and a load on the pharmacist because he needs to dispense medication for this patient and at the same time answer the questions of physician, nurses.' <ref type="figure">(FG5 Pharmacist 4)</ref> One of the nurses also explained that the main cause of errors committed by junior medical staff was workload rather than lack of knowledge.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>' And this is why the medication errors are also increasing, so it's not always related to the knowledge of the resident.</s>
          <s>And if the resident is overloaded because he has to document for all the patients and see all the patients and he is receiving calls from other units as well' (FG3 Nurse 3)</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head n="2.">Lack of staff at key times.</head>
        <p>
          <s>Closely related to workload issues was a critical lack of staff at key times such as weekends and evening which could compromise patient safety.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>'On the whole days of the week, there is complete staff, complete number of physicians.</s>
          <s>In weekend, well, only one physician is doing the whole work.' (FG4 Doctor 2) 'Especially the areas like emergency, less staff.</s>
          <s>They will be get. . .</s>
          <s>too tense by the patients and they just want to do the things for faster.</s>
          <s>so it will make errors.</s>
          <s>
            <ref type="figure">(FG2 Nurse 1)</ref> 3. System-related issues.</s>
          <s>Discussion also centred on key issues related to the systems in operation in various wards and departments.</s>
          <s>There was particular concern over the implementation of Cerner (electronic health record system for hospitals, health care providers, clinics) from doctors, nurses and pharmacists.</s>
          <s>'The electronic system is not robust, and I mean, the hardware is not good enough.' (FG2 Doctor 1) <ref type="bibr">'</ref> We have now to concentrate on the mistakes or medication errors happening by the prescribing system.' (FG5 Pharmacist 2)</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>One senior doctor commented that following implementation of Cerner, fewer checks were being performed compared to the previous paper-based system.</s>
          <s>Themes and subthemes for those behavioural determinants less related to safety culture are summarised in <ref target="#tab_7" type="table">Table 5.</ref> communication openness; handoffs and transitions; and supervisor/manager expectations and actions promoting patient safety.</s>
          <s>During focus group discussions, specific TDF determinants suggested as being potentially associated with these composites were: social/professional role and identity; emotions; and environmental context and resources.</s>
          <s>Thematic analysis identified issues of doctors relying on pharmacists to correct their errors and being reluctant to alter the prescribing of fellow doctors.</s>
          <s>There was a lack of recognition of nurses' roles and frequent policy non-adherence.</s>
          <s>Stress was perceived to be a major contributor to errors, as was excessive workload and lack of staff at key times.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Strengths and weaknesses</head>
        <p>
          <s>The mixed methods design is a key study strength providing quantification of results followed by in-depth explanation.</s>
          <s>Further strengths are the use of the validated HSOPS tool and embedding psychological behaviour change theory (TDF) within qualitative data generation and analysis <ref target="#b14" type="bibr">[15,</ref>
            <ref target="#b18" type="bibr">19]</ref> .</s>
          <s>There are, however, several limitations hence findings should be interpreted with caution.</s>
          <s>Self-reported questionnaire responses could not be validated and may have been impacted by response and social desirability biases <ref target="#b21" type="bibr">[22]</ref> .</s>
          <s>While responses were received from healthcare professionals in all HMC hospitals, these may have been skewed towards females and nurses hence there are potential issues of lack of generalisability within Qatar and beyond.</s>
          <s>Similarly, qualitative findings may not be transferable to other healthcare professionals, settings and countries.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Interpretation</head>
        <p>
          <s>This mixed methods study has contributed to the expressed need for robustness and rigour in patient safety research within the Middle East <ref target="#b19" type="bibr">[20]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Furthermore, it aligns to the WHO 'Global Patient Safety Challenge' calling for action to reduce severe, avoidable medication-related harm by 50% in the next five years <ref target="#b1" type="bibr">[2,</ref>
            <ref target="#b2" type="bibr">3]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Whilst the HSOPS questionnaire has been used within the Middle East <ref target="#b20" type="bibr">[21]</ref> , this is the first study to publish Qatari data.</s>
          <s>There are, however, similarities between the Qatari data and those reported by Elmontsri et al. <ref target="#b20" type="bibr">[21]</ref> , with the lowest agreement scores (and hence of most concern) relating to the composites of non-punitive response to errors; staffing; communication openness; handoffs and transitions; and supervisor/ manager expectations and actions promoting patient safety.</s>
          <s>Within the two composites of lowest scores (non-punitive response to errors and staffing) there were issues with staff perceiving that errors counted against them and that details of errors committed were kept in their personnel files.</s>
          <s>This appeared to be an issue for male, younger and less experienced healthcare professionals.</s>
          <s>Staffing was the other key composite with very low agreement scores, particularly in relation to work pressures and speed of work, with similar statistically significant associations as for the non-punitive response to errors.</s>
          <s>There may be some merit in initially prioritising any intervention towards these specific groupings.</s>
          <s>One limitation of the published studies using the HSOPS is the lack of qualitative research to provide in-depth explanation of the results <ref target="#b20" type="bibr">[21]</ref> .</s>
          <s>The use of behavioural theory within the focus groups in this study identified key determinants which could facilitate intervention development.</s>
          <s>TDF has been incorporated within intervention developments for smoking cessation, physical activity, hand hygiene, acute low back pain and schizophrenia <ref target="#b27" type="bibr">[28]</ref> .</s>
          <s>To date only one other published study has applied TDF to explore potential causes of medication errors, focusing on prescribing errors in a sample of junior doctors in Scotland <ref target="#b28" type="bibr">[29]</ref> .</s>
          <s>There are some similarities with the findings of this study, most notably within the domains of knowledge and skills, particularly the general lack of medication-related knowledge.</s>
          <s>While pharmacists can provide support, and indeed doctors were found to rely on pharmacists to correct errors, the HSOPS data and the focus groups identified issues around staff complement and workload, particularly at key times.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>TDF domains of social/ professional role and identify, emotions and environmental context and resources are related to organisational safety culture, as defined by 'Study Group on Human Factors' <ref target="#b15" type="bibr">[16]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Concerns were expressed around nurses perceiving that their professional role was not recognised leading to poor communication compromising patient safety.</s>
          <s>This is also reflected in the HSOPS score of~50% agreement for communication openness.</s>
          <s>There were instances of doctors relying on pharmacists to correct their prescribing errors and, at times, would not alter the prescribing of others, even when errors could potentially lead to patient harm.</s>
          <s>Themes of environmental context and resources also emerged in the discussions around workload as a leading cause of errors, with lack of staff at key pressure times of evening and weekends.</s>
          <s>Furthermore, the electronic prescribing and records system was considered to have introduced potential for error.</s>
          <s>While such systems have been shown to enhance patient safety, others have also highlighted the risky human factors and user-centred design issues that have been encountered <ref target="#b12" type="bibr">[13]</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Stress was the main theme which emerged in the TDF emotions domain as a determinant of error, arising due to workload, work pressures and the influence of patients.</s>
          <s>Issues of workload were also identified in the HSOPS data around staff numbers to handle the workload, working under pressure to do too much, too quickly.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>These TDF l determinants which were highlighted as potential contributors to medication errors can be used during the development of behaviour change interventions, defined as 'coordinated sets of activities designed to change specified behaviour patterns'.</s>
          <s>These are often complex, consisting of interacting components known as 'behaviour change techniques' (BCTs), 'observable and replicable components designed to change behaviour' <ref target="#b29" type="bibr">[30]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Michie et al. developed a cross-disciplinary taxonomy of evidence based BCTs <ref target="#b30" type="bibr">[31]</ref> , mapped to specific TDF domains <ref target="#b31" type="bibr">[32]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Whilst knowledge and skills can be impacted through education and training <ref target="#b30" type="bibr">[31,</ref>
            <ref target="#b31" type="bibr">32]</ref> , altering aspects of social/ professional role and identity and environmental context and resources are more complex.</s>
          <s>Indeed, the work of Michie et al. <ref target="#b30" type="bibr">[31,</ref>
            <ref target="#b31" type="bibr">32]</ref> did not identify any evidence-based BCTs which mapped reliably to social/professional role and identity.</s>
          <s>Those for environmental context and resources relating mainly to restructuring the physical environment and providing prompts and cues for safer practice, which in this case would focus on the electronic medication systems <ref target="#b30" type="bibr">[31,</ref>
            <ref target="#b31" type="bibr">32]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Rather than focusing on changing behaviour at the individual practitioner level, action may be required at the organisational strategic level to review policies, structures (including resource allocation and distribution) and processes which aim to promote patient safety culture and minimise harm.</s>
          <s>Qualitative research focusing on understanding the perspectives of key strategic decision-makers in relation to promoting all aspects of medication safety is warranted.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Conclusion</head>
        <p>
          <s>This mixed methods study has provided further confirmation of key areas of concern relating to patient safety culture in Qatar.</s>
          <s>Non-punitive response to errors and staffing had the lowest levels of agreement, followed by communication openness, handoffs and transitions, and supervisor/manager expectations and actions.</s>
          <s>The qualitative component provided further detail of specific TDF determinants highlighting issues of social/professional role and identity, emotions, and environmental context and resources.</s>
          <s>Further attention on these issues at strategic and policy levels is required.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Supporting information</head>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Writing -original draft:</head>
        <p>
          <s>Derek Stewart.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <figure xml:id="fig_0">
        <head>Ã</head>
        <label/>
        <figDesc>Communication openness, overall positive response = 50.5% Staff will speak up freely if they see something that may negatively affect patient care 60.9 (agreed) Staff feel free to question the decisions or actions of those with more authority 46.6 (agreed) Ã In this unit, staff are afraid to ask questions when something does not seem right 44.0 (disagreed) Handoffs and transitions, overall positive response = 53.1% Ã Things get missed when transferring patients from one unit to another 53.7 (disagreed) Ã Important patient care information is often lost during shift changes 60.8 (disagreed) Ã Problems often occur in the exchange of information across hospital units 42.9 (disagreed) Ã Shift changes are problematic for patients in this hospital 55.1 (disagreed) Supervisor/manager expectations and actions promoting patient safety, overall positive response = 56.5% My supervisor/ manager says a good word when he/she sees a job done according to established patient safety Whenever pressure builds up, my supervisor/ manager wants us to work faster, even if it means taking shortcuts 46.1 (disagreed) Ã My supervisor/ manager overlooks patient safety problems that happen again and again 31.9 (disagreed) Frequency of events reported, overall positive response = 58.1%</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure xml:id="fig_1">
        <head>'</head>
        <label/>
        <figDesc>Too many patients. Labour ward is full, you know, too many patients for the residents to see.' (FG1 Doctor 2) 'Yeah, I'm working in emergency. So what I feel is it's too much. . . sometime it is too busy and doctors are giving too much orders. . .they cannot to cope with the situation.' (FG1 Nurse 1)</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure xml:id="fig_2">
        <head>'</head>
        <label/>
        <figDesc>Before it was like, when you have the hard copy of medication profile, someone is checking and countersigning. Now in the system, it [checking] is not there as far as I know.' (FG1 Doctor 2)</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure xml:id="fig_3">
        <head>S1</head>
        <label/>
        <figDesc>File. Responses to each of the HSOPS composites. (DOCX) S2 File. Study questionnaire. (DOCX) Supervision: Derek Stewart, Rajvir Singh.</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="false" xml:id="tab_0">
        <head>Table 1 .</head>
        <label>1</label>
        <figDesc>Description of TDF domains (adapted from Cain et al. [15]).</figDesc>
        <table>TDF Domains 
Description 

Knowledge 
An awareness of the existence of something 

Skills 
An ability or proficiency acquired through practice 

Social/Professional Role and 
Identity 

A coherent set of behaviours and displayed personal qualities of an individual in 
a social or work setting 

Beliefs about Capabilities 
Acceptance of the truth, reality, or validity about an ability, talent, or facility that 
a person can put to constructive use 

Optimism 
The confidence that things will happen for the best or that desired goals will be 
attained 

Beliefs about Consequences 
Acceptance of the truth, reality, or validity about outcomes of a behaviour in a 
given situation 

Reinforcement 
Increasing the probability of a response by arranging a dependent relationship, 
or contingency, between the response and a given stimulus 

Intentions 
A conscious decision to perform a behaviour or a resolve to act in a certain way 

Goals 
Mental representations of outcomes or end states that an individual wants to 
achieve 

Memory, Attention and Decision 
Processes 

The ability to retain information, focus selectively on aspects of the environment 
and choose between two or more alternatives 

Environmental Context and 
Resources 

Any circumstance of a person's situation or environment that discourages or 
encourages the development of skills and abilities, independence, social 
competence, and adaptive behaviour 

Social Influences 
Those interpersonal processes that can cause individuals to change their 
thoughts, feelings, or behaviours 

Emotion 
A complex reaction pattern, involving experiential, behavioural, and 
physiological elements, by which the individual attempts to deal with a 
personally significant matter or event 

Behavioural Regulation or 
measured actions 

Anything aimed at managing or changing objectively observed 

https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0204801.t001 

Perspectives of healthcare professionals in Qatar on causes of medication errors 

</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="false" xml:id="tab_1">
        <head>Table 2 .</head>
        <label>2</label>
        <figDesc>HSOPS composites and definitions<ref target="#b18" type="bibr">[19]</ref>.</figDesc>
        <table>Composite 
Definition: The extent to which. . . 

Communication openness 
staff freely speak up if they see something that may negatively affect a 
patient and feel free to question those with more authority 

Feedback and communication about 
error 

staff are informed about errors that happen, are given feedback about 
changes implemented, and discuss ways to prevent errors 

Frequency of events reported 
mistakes of the following types are reported: mistakes caught and corrected 
before affecting the patient; mistakes with no potential to harm the patient; 
and mistakes that could harm the patient but do not 

Handoffs and transitions 
important patient care information is transferred across hospital units and 
during shift changes 

Management support for patient 
safety 

hospital management provides a work climate that promotes patient safety 
and shows that patient safety top priority 

Non-punitive response to error 
staff feel that their mistakes and event reports are not held against them and 
that mistakes are not kept in their personnel file 

Organisational learning-continuous 
improvement 

mistakes have led to positive changes and changes evaluated for 
effectiveness 

Overall perceptions of patient safety 
procedures and systems are good at preventing errors and there is a lack of 
patient safety problems 

Staffing 
there are enough staff to handle the workload and work hours are 
appropriate to provide the best care for patients 

Supervisor/manager expectations and 
actions promoting patient safety 

supervisors/managers consider staff suggestions for improving patient 
safety, praise staff for following patient safety procedures, and do not 
overlook patient safety problems 

Teamwork across units 
hospital units cooperate and coordinate with one another to provide the 
best care for patients 

Teamwork within units 
staff support each other, treat each other with respect, and work together as 
a team 

https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0204801.t002 

Perspectives of healthcare professionals in Qatar on causes of medication errors 

</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="true" xml:id="tab_2">
        <head>Table 3 .</head>
        <label>3</label>
        <figDesc>Respondents' demographic and professional characteristics (N = 1604).</figDesc>
        <table>Characteristic 
Percentage 
Frequency, n 

Current role in the hospital 

Clinical nurse educator 
0.7 
12 

Clinical pharmacist 
2.8 
45 

Consultant physician 
5.4 
86 

Head/Charge/Specialist nurse 
17.1 
275 

Nurse 
50.0 
802 

Pharmacist 
8.9 
143 

Pharmacy Director/Supervisor/Specialist 
1.2 
19 

Resident Physician 
3.5 
56 

Specialist Physician 
4.5 
72 

Other 
5.0 
80 

Missing 
0.9 
14 

Age (years) 

29 
24.2 
392 

30-39 
41.8 
670 

40-49 
21.5 
345 

50-59 
9.5 
153 

!60 
1.6 
25 

Missing 
1.7 
19 

Gender 

Male 
27.6 
442 

Female 
70.9 
1137 

Missing 
1.6 
25 

Country of receiving entry-to-practice degree 

India 
42.7 
685 

Philippines 
17.6 
283 

Egypt 
9.3 
149 

Qatar 
9.2 
148 

Jordan 
4.8 
77 

Other 
14.5 
231 

Missing 
1.9 
31 

Experience as healthcare professional in hospital (years) 

&lt;1 
1.6 
25 

1-5 
19.1 
306 

6-10 
29.4 
471 

11-15 
21.4 
343 

16-20 
12.0 
193 

&gt;20 
14.7 
235 

Missing 
1.9 
31 

Experience as healthcare professional in Qatar (years) 

&lt;1 
8.5 
136 

1-5 
40.3 
647 

6-10 
21.8 
350 

11-15 
16.5 
264 

16-20 
5.1 
82 

&gt;20 
6.7 
108 

Missing 
1.1 
17 

(Continued) 
</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="false" xml:id="tab_3">
        <head>Table 3 .</head>
        <label>3</label>
        <figDesc>(Continued)    </figDesc>
        <table>Characteristic 
Percentage 
Frequency, n 

Hours worked in a typical week 

&lt;20 
1.3 
21 

20-39 
10.6 
170 

40-59 
82.7 
1326 

!60 
3.0 
48 

Missing 
2.4 
39 

In your role you typically have direct interaction or contact with patients 

Yes 
85.6 
1373 

No 
9.0 
145 

Missing 
5.4 
86 

Your primary roles in the medicines process are (multiple options could be chosen) 

Prescribing 
15.1 
243 

Administering 
61.1 
980 

Preparation and Dispensing 
25.9 
415 

Monitoring 
42.0 
673 

Missing 
3.1 
49 

https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0204801.t003 

Perspectives of healthcare professionals in Qatar on causes of medication errors 

</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="true" xml:id="tab_4">
        <head>Table 4 .</head>
        <label>4</label>
        <figDesc>Positive responses to HSOPS items and composites (N = 1604).</figDesc>
        <table>Statements 
% positive response 
(100% representing the highest positive 
response to each statement) 

Non-punitive response to errors, overall positive response = 24.0% ÃÃ 
Ã Staff feel like errors count against them 
26.2 (disagreed) 
Ã When an error is reported, it feels like the person is being reported, 
not the problem 

31.1 (disagreed) 

Ã Staff worry that errors they make are kept in their personnel file 
14.6 (disagreed) 

Staffing, overall positive response = 36.2% 

We have enough staff to handle the workload 
54.7 (agreed) 
Ã We use more locum staff than is best for patient care 
30.5 (disagreed) 
Ã We work under pressure trying to do too much, too quickly 
23.5 (disagreed) 

</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="false" xml:id="tab_6">
        <head>Table 4 .</head>
        <label>4</label>
        <figDesc>(Continued) Lack of recognition of the role of nurses. Some of the nurses described that they were often omitted from discussions around patient care and decision making, even when present on ward rounds or meetings. There were instances where discussions took place in a different language,'Even I'm noting that during the rounds, team decisions, the nurses are not informed. Sometimes they [the doctors] are discussing in Arabic. The nurse, she cannot understand their plan and what is the decision.' (FG3 Nurse 1) 4. Policy non-adherence. Health professionals not adhering to various policies was considered a cause of medication errors, 'Not abiding the. . . complying with the policies' (FG2 Doctor 2) 'There are seven or eight points that the pharmacist should check. If the pharmacist, for example, dispensed the wrong medication it means that he didn't follow the policy.' (FG5 Pharmacist 4)</figDesc>
        <table>Statements 
% positive response 
(100% representing the highest positive 
response to each statement) 

We are informed about medication errors in this unit 
62.0 (agreed) 

In this unit, we discuss ways to prevent medication errors from 
happening again 

68.0 (agreed) 

Teamwork across units, overall positive response = 67.7% 

There is good cooperation among hospital units that need to work 
together 

72.9 (agreed) 

Hospital units work well together to provide the best care for patients 82.8 (agreed) 
Ã Hospital units do not coordinate well with each other 
57.5 (disagreed) 
Ã It is often unpleasant to work with staff from other hospital units 
57.5 (disagreed) 

Management support for patient safety, overall positive response = 75.4% 

Hospital management provides a work environment that promotes 
patient safety 

87.0 (agreed) 

The actions of hospital management show that patient safety is a top 
priority 

84.2 (agreed) 

Hospital management seems interested in patient safety only after an 
error happens 

54.9 (agreed) 

Teamwork within units, overall positive response = 82.1% 

People support one another in this unit 
81.1 (agreed) 

When a lot of work needs to be done quickly, we work as a team to 
get the work done 

83.4 (agreed) 

In this unit, people treat each other with respect 
81.9 (agreed) 

Organisational learning-continuous improvement, Overall positive 
response = 85.8% 

We are actively doing things to improve patient safety 
90.2 (agreed) 

After we make changes to improve patient safety, we evaluate their 
effectiveness 

81.3 (agreed) 

Ã Reverse scored negatively worded statement 

ÃÃ Calculated from the mean items within each composite 

https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0204801.t004 

Perspectives of healthcare professionals in Qatar on causes of medication errors 

</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="false" xml:id="tab_7">
        <head>Table 5 .</head>
        <label>5</label>
        <figDesc>A summary of TDF domains and themes (less related to culture) relating to causes of medication errors. There is too much error in this area, they can provide another or a new continuous education for this field. It's very important and this can prevent such error.' (FG7 Nurse 1)Skills1. Suboptimal medication related skills 'We need to think about the administration. I have seen plenty of times the paper on which they [nurses] have written the calculation and it's wrong, actually most of the time.' (FG4 Pharmacist 1) Beliefs about Capabilities 1. Lack of medication related competence 'But you think it's. . . it's. . . it's valid to let the nurses check the dose before administering? No, I don't think it's possible. For me, I feel it's impossible for them to check the correct dose.' (FG1 Doctor 1) 2. Overconfidence leading to medication errors 'Overconfidence with some particular medicines like I have been with this medicine for many years and I know by heart' (FG1 Pharmacist 2)</figDesc>
        <table>TDF Domain 
Subtheme 
Illustrative quotes 

Knowledge 
1. Lack of medication related knowledge 
'So coming to the nursing knowledge regarding the dose. I will never believe they have that 
much knowledge about the doses. . .' (FG1 Doctor 1) 

2. Knowledge is limited to a particular 
speciality/area 

'If we're dealing with the general hospital, medicine department they have good orientation 
regarding medication, but if you go to ortho [orthopaedics] or surgery, really their knowledge 
about medication is very low.' (FG5 Pharmacist 3) 

3. Lack of knowledge attributed to staff 
induction 

'Proper induction, you know, they should have proper induction regarding the medication, the 
medications that are used, how you do the checking and things like that. Nothing is done.' 
(FG1 Doctor 2) 

4. Need for continuing professional 
development to reduce medication errors 

'</table>
      </figure>
      <note place="foot">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0204801September 28, 2018  </note>
      <note place="foot">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0204801 September 28, 2018 7 / 17</note>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="acknowledgement">
        <div>
          <head>Acknowledgments</head>
          <p>
            <s>The authors wish to acknowledge the contributions of all questionnaire respondents and focus group participants, as well as support departments at Hamad Medical Corporation, Doha, Qatar.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Author Contributions</head>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="references">
        <listBibl>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b0">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">The global burden of unsafe medical care: analytic modelling of observational studies</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">K</forename>
                  <surname>Jha</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">I</forename>
                  <surname>Larizgoitia</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <surname>Audera-Lopez</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">N</forename>
                  <surname>Prasopa-Plaizier</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">H</forename>
                  <surname>Waters</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">W</forename>
                  <surname>Bates</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjqs-2012-001748</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjqs-2012-001748PMID"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">BMJ Qual Saf</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">24048616</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2013"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b1">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">World Health Organization. Medication Without Harm, WHO Global Patient Safety Challenge. Geneva: World Health Organization</title>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2017"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b2">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Medication Without Harm: WHO's Third Global Patient Safety Challenge</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">L</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">J</forename>
                  <surname>Donaldson</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">E</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">T</forename>
                  <surname>Kelley</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">N</forename>
                  <surname>Dhingra-Kumar</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">P</forename>
                  <surname>Kieny</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <surname>Sheikh</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0140-6736(17)31047-4</idno>
              <idno type="PMID">28463129</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Lancet</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">389</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="31047" to="31051" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2017"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b3">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Prevalence, incidence and nature of prescribing errors in hospital inpatients</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">P</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">J</forename>
                  <surname>Lewis</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">T</forename>
                  <surname>Dornan</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <surname>Taylor</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">P</forename>
                  <surname>Tully</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">V</forename>
                  <surname>Wass</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">M</forename>
                  <surname>Ashcroft</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.2165/00002018-200932050-00002</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.2165/00002018-200932050-00002PMID"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Drug Saf</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">19419233</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2009"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b4">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">What is the scale of prescribing errors committed by junior doctors? A systematic review</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Ross</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <surname>Bond</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">H</forename>
                  <surname>Rothnie</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Thomas</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">J</forename>
                  <surname>Macleod</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Brit J Clin Pharmacol</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="629" to="669" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2009"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b5">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Incidence, type and causes of dispensing errors: a review of the literature</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">K</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">L</forename>
                  <surname>James</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <surname>Barlow</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <surname>Mcartney</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Hiom</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <surname>Roberts</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <surname>Whittlesea</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="PMID">20218026</idno>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Int J Pharm Pract</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="9" to="30" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2009"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b6">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Prescribing errors in hospital inpatients: a three-centre study of their prevalence, types and causes</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">B</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">D</forename>
                  <surname>Franklin</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Reynolds</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">N</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">A</forename>
                  <surname>Shebl</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Burnett</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">Jacklin</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">A</forename>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.1136/pgmj.2011.117879</idno>
              <idno type="PMID">21757461</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1136/pgmj.2011.117879"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Postgrad Med J</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="739" to="784" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2011"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b7">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Prevalence and nature of medication administration errors in health care settings: a systematic review of direct observational evidence</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">N</forename>
                  <surname>Keers</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">D</forename>
                  <surname>Williams</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Cooke</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">M</forename>
                  <surname>Ashcroft</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.1345/aph.1R147</idno>
              <idno type="PMID">23386063</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1345/aph.1R147"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Ann Pharmacother</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="237" to="56" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2013"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b8">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">National Coordinating Council for Medication Error Reporting and Prevention</title>
              <ptr target="http://www.nccmerp.org"/>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2017-06"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b9">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">The causes of and factors associated with prescribing errors in hospital inpatients</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">P</forename>
                  <surname>Tully</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">M</forename>
                  <surname>Ashcroft</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">T</forename>
                  <surname>Dornan</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">P</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">J</forename>
                  <surname>Lewis</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <surname>Taylor</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">V</forename>
                  <surname>Wass</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.2165/11316560-000000000-00000</idno>
              <idno type="PMID">19722726</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Drug Saf</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="819" to="855" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2009"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b10">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">The incidence, prevalence and contributing factors associated with the occurrence of medication errors for children and adults in the community setting: A systematic review</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">K</forename>
                  <surname>Sears</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <surname>Ross-White</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">M</forename>
                  <surname>Godfrey</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">JBI Database Syst Rev Implement</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="2350" to="464" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2012"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b11">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Causes of medication administration errors in hospitals: a systematic review of quantitative and qualitative evidence</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">N</forename>
                  <surname>Keers</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">D</forename>
                  <surname>Williams</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Cooke</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">M</forename>
                  <surname>Ashcroft</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.1007/s40264-013-0090-2</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s40264-013-0090-2PMID"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Drug Saf</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">23975331</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2013"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b12">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">A systematic review of the types and causes of prescribing errors generated from using computerized provider order entry systems in primary and secondary care</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">L</forename>
                  <surname>Brown</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">H</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">L</forename>
                  <surname>Mulcaster</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">K</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">L</forename>
                  <surname>Triffitt</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">F</forename>
                  <surname>Sittig</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">S</forename>
                  <surname>Ash</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">K</forename>
                  <surname>Reygate</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J Am Med Inform</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="page">119</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2016"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b13">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Developing and evaluating complex interventions: the new Medical Research Council guidance</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">P</forename>
                  <surname>Craig</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">P</forename>
                  <surname>Dieppe</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Macintyre</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Michie</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">I</forename>
                  <surname>Nazareth</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Petticrew</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">BMJ</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">337</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">1665</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2008"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b14">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Validation of the theoretical domains framework for use in behaviour change and implementation research</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Cane</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <surname>O&amp;apos;connor</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Michie</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.1186/1748-5908-7-37</idno>
              <idno type="PMID">22530986</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1186/1748-5908-7-37"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Implement Sci</title>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2012"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b15">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m">Study Group on Human Factors. Organising for safety: third report of the ACSNI (Advisory Committee on the Safety of Nuclear Installations). England: HSE Books</title>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="1993"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b16">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Strategies for improving patient safety culture in hospitals: a systematic review</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">T</forename>
                  <surname>Morello</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">A</forename>
                  <surname>Lowthian</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">L</forename>
                  <surname>Barker</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <surname>Mcginnes</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <surname>Dunt</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <surname>Brand</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjqs-2011-000582</idno>
              <idno type="PMID">22849965</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjqs-2011-000582"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">BMJ Qual Saf</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="11" to="18" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2013"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b17">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Promoting a culture of safety as a patient safety strategy: a systematic review</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">J</forename>
                  <surname>Weaver</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">L</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">H</forename>
                  <surname>Lubomksi</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">F</forename>
                  <surname>Wilson</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">E</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">R</forename>
                  <surname>Pfoh</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">K</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">A</forename>
                  <surname>Martinez</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">M</forename>
                  <surname>Dy</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.7326/0003-4819-158-5-201303051-00002</idno>
              <idno type="PMID">23460092</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Ann Intern Med</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="369" to="374" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2013"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b18">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">AHRQ Hospital Survey on Patient Safety Culture: User's Guide. (Prepared by Westat, under Contract No. HHSA290201300003C)</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Sorra</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">L</forename>
                  <surname>Gray</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Streagle</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">T</forename>
                  <surname>Famolaro</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">N</forename>
                  <surname>Yount</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Behm</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno>15-0049-EF (Replaces 04-0041</idno>
              <ptr target="http://www.ahrq.gov/professionals/quality-patient-safety/patientsafetyculture/hospital/index.html"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="m">Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality</title>
              <meeting>
                <address>
                  <addrLine>Rockville, MD</addrLine>
                </address>
              </meeting>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2017-06"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
            <note>accessed</note>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b19">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Medication errors in the Middle East countries: a systematic review of the literature</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">Z</forename>
                  <surname>Alsulami</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Conroy</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">I</forename>
                  <surname>Choonara</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00228-012-1435-y</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00228-012-1435-yPMID"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Eur J Clin Pharmacol</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">23090705</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2013"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b20">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Status of patient safety culture in Arab countries: a systematic review</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Elmontsri</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <surname>Almashrafi</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <surname>Banarsee</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <surname>Majeed</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013487</idno>
              <idno type="PMID">28237956</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2016-013487"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">BMJ Open</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2017"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b21">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">Choosing a mixed method design. Designing and conducting mixed method research</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Creswell</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">V</forename>
                  <surname>Clark</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2006"/>
                <publisher>SAGE Inc</publisher>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b22">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Combining the power of stories and the power of numbers: mixed methods research and mixed studies reviews</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">P</forename>
                  <surname>Pluye</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">Q</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">N</forename>
                  <surname>Hong</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev-publhealth-032013-182440</idno>
              <idno type="PMID">24188053</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-publhealth-032013-182440"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Annu Rev Public Health</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="29" to="45" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2014"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b23">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Organizational research: Determining appropriate sample size in survey research</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">E</forename>
                  <surname>Barlett</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">W</forename>
                  <surname>Kotrlik</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">C</forename>
                  <surname>Higgins</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Inf Technol Learn Perform J</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">43</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2001"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b24">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Strategies for ensuring trustworthiness in qualitative research projects</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">K</forename>
                  <surname>Shenton</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Educ Inform</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="63" to="67" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2004"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b25">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Are we there yet? Data saturation in qualitative research</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">P</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">I</forename>
                  <surname>Fusch</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">L</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">R</forename>
                  <surname>Ness</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Qual Rep</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">1408</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2015"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b26">
            <monogr>
              <title level="m" type="main">Qualitative data analysis for applied policy research. The Qualitative Researcher's Companion</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Ritchie</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">L</forename>
                  <surname>Spencer</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2002"/>
                <biblScope from="305" to="329" unit="page"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b27">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Theories of behaviour change synthesised into a set of theoretical groupings: introducing a thematic series on the theoretical domains framework</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">J</forename>
                  <surname>Francis</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <surname>O&amp;apos;connor</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Curran</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.1186/1748-5908-7-35</idno>
              <idno type="PMID">22531601</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1186/1748-5908-7-35"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Implement Sci</title>
              <imprint>
                <date type="published" when="2012"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b28">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Learning curves, taking instructions, and patient safety: using a theoretical domains framework in an interview study to investigate prescribing errors among trainee doctors</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">E</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">M</forename>
                  <surname>Duncan</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">J</forename>
                  <surname>Francis</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Johnston</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">P</forename>
                  <surname>Davey</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Maxwell</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">G</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">A</forename>
                  <surname>Mckay</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Implement Sci</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">86</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2012"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b29">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">The behaviour change wheel: a new method for characterising and designing behaviour change interventions</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Michie</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">M</forename>
                  <surname>Van Stralen</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <surname>West</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.1186/1748-5908-6-42</idno>
              <idno type="PMID">21513547</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1186/1748-5908-6-42"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Implement Sci</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">42</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2011"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b30">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">The behavior change technique taxonomy (v1) of 93 hierarchically clustered techniques: building an international consensus for the reporting of behavior change interventions</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Michie</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Richardson</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Johnston</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <surname>Abraham</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Francis</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">W</forename>
                  <surname>Hardeman</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <idno type="DOI">10.1007/s12160-013-9486-6</idno>
              <ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12160-013-9486-6PMID"/>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Ann Behav Med</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">23512568</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2013"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b31">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Behaviour change techniques: the development and evaluation of a taxonomic method for reporting and describing behaviour change interventions (a suite of five studies involving consensus methods, randomised controlled trials and analysis of qualitative data)</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Michie</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">E</forename>
                  <surname>Wood</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Johnston</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <surname>Abraham</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Francis</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">W</forename>
                  <surname>Hardeman</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Health Technol Assess</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2015"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
