<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/lopez/grobid/dataseer-ml/../grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="GROBID" version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" when="2019-07-08T07:40+0000">
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a" type="main">Platinum-trimer decorated cobalt-palladium core-shell nanocatalyst with promising performance for oxygen reduction reaction</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher/>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <licence/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Sheng</forename>
                <surname>Dai</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff0">
                <orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
                <address>
                  <postCode>92697</postCode>
                  <settlement>Irvine</settlement>
                  <region>CA</region>
                  <country key="US">USA</country>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Jyh-Pin</forename>
                <surname>Chou</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff1">
                <orgName type="department">Department of Mechanical and Biomedical Engineering</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">City University of Hong Kong</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Kowloon, Hong Kong</settlement>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Kuan-Wen</forename>
                <surname>Wang</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff2">
                <orgName type="department">Institute of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">National Central University</orgName>
                <address>
                  <postCode>32001</postCode>
                  <settlement>Taoyuan</settlement>
                  <country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Yang-Yang</forename>
                <surname>Hsu</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff3">
                <orgName type="department">Department of Engineering and System Science</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">National Tsing Hua University</orgName>
                <address>
                  <postCode>30013</postCode>
                  <settlement>Hsinchu</settlement>
                  <country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Alice</forename>
                <surname>Hu</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff1">
                <orgName type="department">Department of Mechanical and Biomedical Engineering</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">City University of Hong Kong</orgName>
                <address>
                  <settlement>Kowloon, Hong Kong</settlement>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Xiaoqing</forename>
                <surname>Pan</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff0">
                <orgName type="department">Department of Materials Science and Engineering</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
                <address>
                  <postCode>92697</postCode>
                  <settlement>Irvine</settlement>
                  <region>CA</region>
                  <country key="US">USA</country>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
              <affiliation key="aff4">
                <orgName type="department">Department of Physics and Astronomy</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
                <address>
                  <postCode>92697</postCode>
                  <settlement>Irvine</settlement>
                  <region>CA</region>
                  <country key="US">USA</country>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
              <affiliation key="aff5">
                <orgName key="instit1" type="institution">Irvine Materials Research Institute (IMRI)</orgName>
                <orgName key="instit2" type="institution">University of California</orgName>
                <address>
                  <postCode>92697</postCode>
                  <settlement>Irvine</settlement>
                  <region>CA</region>
                  <country key="US">USA</country>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename type="first">Tsan-Yao</forename>
                <surname>Chen</surname>
              </persName>
              <affiliation key="aff3">
                <orgName type="department">Department of Engineering and System Science</orgName>
                <orgName type="institution">National Tsing Hua University</orgName>
                <address>
                  <postCode>30013</postCode>
                  <settlement>Hsinchu</settlement>
                  <country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
                </address>
              </affiliation>
            </author>
            <title level="a" type="main">Platinum-trimer decorated cobalt-palladium core-shell nanocatalyst with promising performance for oxygen reduction reaction</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <imprint>
              <date/>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          <idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41467-019-08323-w</idno>
          <note>ARTICLE OPEN 7 Institute of Nuclear Engineering and Science, National Tsing Hua University, Hsinchu 30013, Taiwan. 8 Higher Education Sprout Project, Competitive Research Team, National Tsing Hua University, Hsinchu 30013, Taiwan. 9 Hierarchical Green-Energy Materials Research Center, National Cheng Kung University, Tainan 70101, Taiwan. Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to T.-Y.C. (</note>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <abstract>
        <div>
          <p>
            <s>Advanced electrocatalysts with low platinum content, high activity and durability for the oxygen reduction reaction can benefit the widespread commercial use of fuel cell technology.</s>
            <s>Here, we report a platinum-trimer decorated cobalt-palladium core-shell nanocatalyst with a low platinum loading of only 2.4 wt% for the use in alkaline fuel cell cathodes.</s>
            <s>This ternary catalyst shows a mass activity that is enhanced by a factor of 30.6 relative to a commercial platinum catalyst, which is attributed to the unique charge localization induced by platinumtrimer decoration.</s>
            <s>The high stability of the decorated trimers endows the catalyst with an outstanding durability, maintaining decent electrocatalytic activity with no degradation for more than 322,000 potential cycles in alkaline electrolyte.</s>
            <s>These findings are expected to be useful for surface engineering and design of advanced fuel cell catalysts with atomic-scale platinum decoration.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
      </abstract>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div>
        <p>
          <s>F uel cells, which convert chemical energy from a fuel into electricity through an electrochemical reaction, are promising for stationary power generation and transportation, and thus may help solve global problems of energy supply and clean environment <ref target="#b0" type="bibr">[1]</ref>
            <ref target="#b1" type="bibr">[2]</ref>
            <ref target="#b2" type="bibr">[3]</ref>
            <ref target="#b3" type="bibr">[4]</ref> .</s>
          <s>However, the sluggish kinetics of the oxygen reduction reaction (ORR) at the cathode, and the high cost of Pt used in electrocatalysts pose obstacles to the commercial viability of this technology <ref target="#b4" type="bibr">[5]</ref>
            <ref target="#b5" type="bibr">[6]</ref>
            <ref target="#b6" type="bibr">[7]</ref> .</s>
          <s>In the past decades, substantial efforts have been devoted to developing high-performance electrocatalysts with minimal Pt content, through the control of particle size, morphology, chemical composition, and surface configuration <ref target="#b7" type="bibr">[8]</ref>
            <ref target="#b8" type="bibr">[9]</ref>
            <ref target="#b9" type="bibr">[10]</ref>
            <ref target="#b10" type="bibr">[11]</ref>
            <ref target="#b11" type="bibr">[12]</ref> .</s>
          <s>For example, alloying Pt and non-noble metals (e.g., Fe, Co, Ni) reduces the Pt usage in electrocatalysts while improving their intrinsic ORR activity, in comparison with the pure Pt catalysts <ref target="#b11" type="bibr">[12]</ref>
            <ref target="#b12" type="bibr">[13]</ref>
            <ref target="#b13" type="bibr">[14]</ref> ; decorating Pt overlayers on metal nanoparticles is another strategy to achieve decent ORR performance at a low Pt content <ref target="#b14" type="bibr">[15]</ref>
            <ref target="#b15" type="bibr">[16]</ref>
            <ref target="#b16" type="bibr">[17]</ref>
            <ref target="#b17" type="bibr">[18]</ref>
            <ref target="#b18" type="bibr">[19]</ref>
            <ref target="#b19" type="bibr">[20]</ref>
            <ref target="#b20" type="bibr">[21]</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Besides the improved ORR activity in these advanced studies <ref target="#b11" type="bibr">[12]</ref>
            <ref target="#b12" type="bibr">[13]</ref>
            <ref target="#b13" type="bibr">[14]</ref>
            <ref target="#b14" type="bibr">[15]</ref>
            <ref target="#b15" type="bibr">[16]</ref>
            <ref target="#b16" type="bibr">[17]</ref>
            <ref target="#b17" type="bibr">[18]</ref>
            <ref target="#b18" type="bibr">[19]</ref>
            <ref target="#b19" type="bibr">[20]</ref>
            <ref target="#b20" type="bibr">[21]</ref> , there is still room for higher Pt utilization efficiency at the atomic level in ORR catalysts <ref target="#b21" type="bibr">22</ref> .</s>
          <s>In addition, it is notable that durability is an even more critical issue of the application of ORR catalysts since the agglomeration and surface corrosion of nanoparticles always result in a rapid loss of the ORR performance <ref target="#b22" type="bibr">[23]</ref>
            <ref target="#b23" type="bibr">[24]</ref>
            <ref target="#b24" type="bibr">[25]</ref> .</s>
          <s>Therefore, designing and synthesizing novel ORR catalysts that possess high catalytic activity and durability with a low Pt content remains an important challenge.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>In an attempt to address these critical issues of ORR nanocatalysts, we report a new design configuration of a ternary Co-PdPt catalyst at a low Pt loading of 2.4%, where Pt trimer (Pt 3 ) species are decorated on a Co-Pd core-shell (Co@Pd) structure.</s>
          <s>This ternary catalyst shows an ORR mass activity that is enhanced by a factor of 30.6 relative to a commercial Pt catalyst.</s>
          <s>In particular, the Co-Pd-Pt catalyst exhibits an outstanding durability, maintaining its high activity for over 322,000 potential cycles in alkaline electrolyte due to the survival and dispersion of the decorated Pt 3 species during ORR.</s>
          <s>Theoretical calculations reveal a unique charge localization on the ternary catalyst surface, induced by the Pt 3 decoration, thus weakening the chemisorbed anions and improving the ORR performance.</s>
          <s>These findings should help pave the way for atomic-scale surface engineering and design of advanced ORR nanocatalysts used in alkaline fuel cells.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Results</head>
        <p>
          <s>Sample preparation.</s>
          <s>A carbon nanotube (CNT)-supported ternary Co-Pd-Pt nanocatalyst (Co@Pd-Pt/CNT), consisting of a Co@Pd core-shell structure and surface decoration of Pt <ref target="#b2" type="bibr">3</ref> , was synthesized via a developed wet chemical reduction method <ref target="#b25" type="bibr">26</ref> , following a controlled sequence of Co nanoparticle formation, Pd shell growth, and Pt decoration.</s>
          <s>Particularly, the reaction time of the final step of Pt decoration was restricted within 10 s for a precise control of the Pt 3 decoration (detailed synthetic approaches are described in Methods and Supplementary Notes 1 and 2).</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>In addition, control samples, including CNT-supported Co (Co/CNT), CNT-supported Pt (Pt/CNT), CNT-supported Pd (Pd/CNT), CNT-supported Co-Pd core-shell (Co@Pd/CNT), CNT-supported Co-Pt core-shell (Co@Pt/CNT), and CNTsupported Pd-Pt core-shell (Pd@Pt/CNT) catalysts were also prepared through similar synthetic procedures for comparison and analysis.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Electron microscopy.</s>
          <s>Aberration-corrected scanning transmission electron microscopy (AC-STEM) was utilized to reveal morphology and structure information of the as-synthesized Co@Pd-Pt/CNT nanocatalyst.</s>
          <s>
            <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Figure 1</ref> shows the typical result of high angle annular dark field (HAADF)-STEM imaging and energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (EDS).</s>
          <s>As illustrated by the EDS elemental maps in <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Fig. 1b</ref> , c, a structure of a Co-rich core and a Pd-rich shell is well reflected (more STEM results showing the Co@Pd core-shell structure are provided in <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Supplementary Fig. 1</ref> ).</s>
          <s>According to the atomic-scale STEM image, the Pd shell exhibits a unconformable characteristic, showing various crystal orientations on the Co core, as indicated by the red arrows in <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Fig. 1a</ref> .</s>
          <s>Moreover, the decorated Pt species can be directly observed in the HAADF-STEM image due to the highest Zcontrast <ref target="#b26" type="bibr">27</ref> (indicated by the yellow arrows in <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Fig. 1a)</ref> , and further confirmed by the EDS elemental map in <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Fig. 1d</ref> .</s>
          <s>Based on typical STEM results (see <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Supplementary Figs. 1 and 2)</ref> , it is noticeable that the decorated Pt species show a fuzzy feature, instead of clear lattice fringes, indicating its unique structure on the Co@Pd nanoparticle surface.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>According to the semi-quantitative EDS analysis, chemical composition of the Co@Pd-Pt nanoparticles is revealed as 52.1% of Co, 43.4% of Pd, and 4.5% of Pt (weight ratio).</s>
          <s>Moreover, X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS) shows that the surface composition of the as-synthesized nanoparticles is 3.9% of Co, 49.2% of Pd, and 46.9% of Pt on average, within a probing depth around 1.5 nm (see <ref target="#tab_0" type="table">Supplementary Figs. 3-5 and Supplementary Table 1)</ref> , confirming the structure of surface Pt-decorated Co-Pd core-shell nanoparticles.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>X-ray absorption spectroscopy.</s>
          <s>For a deeper understanding of the unique structure of the ternary Co@Pd-Pt catalyst, X-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS) was carried out while representative control samples were also analyzed.</s>
          <s>For example, <ref target="#fig_1" type="figure">Fig. 2a</ref> shows the normalized Pt L 3 -edge X-ray absorption near-edge spectra (XANES) of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst, while the spectra of Pt/CNT, Pd@Pt/CNT, and the reference sample (Pt foil) are also provided for comparison.</s>
          <s>As indicated by the black arrow in <ref target="#fig_1" type="figure">Fig. 2a</ref> , the position of the inflection point in XANES refers to the threshold energy for 2p to 5d electron transition, and is generally proportional to the oxidation state of Pt.</s>
          <s>Clearly, positions of the inflection point of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT, Pd@Pt/CNT, and Pt/CNT catalysts are all identical to that of Pt foil, demonstrating the metallic characteristics of Pt atoms in these materials (more details can be found in <ref target="#fig_6" type="figure">Supplementary Fig. 6</ref> showing the derivative XANES spectra in the near-edge region).</s>
          <s>Moreover, the relative extent of empty states and the splitting of Pt 5d 5/2 orbital can be revealed through the intensity (H A ) and the width (W A ) of the main absorption peak, as illustrated in <ref target="#fig_1" type="figure">Fig. 2a</ref> .</s>
          <s>For example, compared to that of Pt foil, the absorption intensity of Pt/CNT sample (the red line) show an increment, corresponding to the oxygen chemisorption due to an absence of surface stabilization.</s>
          <s>As for the Pd@Pt/CNT sample (the blue line), a substantial increment of the absorption intensity shows that majority of the coordination sites of Pt atoms are occupied by oxygen chemisorption in this catalyst sample.</s>
          <s>However, the Co@Pd-Pt/CNT nanocatalyst (the green line) represents a much lower H A , demonstrating a strong charge localization from the Co@Pd surface to the decorated Pt species, while the narrowest width W A reflects the lowest extent of 5d 5/2 splitting among these catalyst samples.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>In addition, features in the post edge of XANES spectra, corresponding to the interference of photoelectrons with local atoms, are usually used to describe the extent of local structural ordering around the target atom.</s>
          <s>As shown in the inset of <ref target="#fig_1" type="figure">Fig. 2a</ref> , a major difference is revealed between the Pt-decorated catalysts (Pd@Pt/CNT and Co@Pd-Pt/CNT) and the Pt-based samples (Pt/CNT and Pt foil) that the intensity of the oscillation hump (H p ) decreases along with broadening of the width (W p ) of the hump in the previous two catalysts, indicating disordered structures around the decorated Pt species.</s>
          <s>Particularly, a significantly attenuated H p and a broadened W p of the Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalysts (see the green line in the inset of <ref target="#fig_1" type="figure">Fig. 2a</ref> ) denote the presence of high-density local defects around Pt atoms on the Co@Pd surface.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Quantitative atomic structural parameters around the Pt atoms are further revealed by model analysis of extended X-ray absorption fine structure (EXAFS).</s>
          <s>
            <ref target="#fig_1" type="figure">Figure 2b</ref> presents the Fourier-transformed extended X-ray absorption fine structure (FT-EXAFS) spectra (radial structure function, RSF) of Pt L 3 -edge of the four samples, and corresponding structural parameters are summarized in <ref target="#tab_0" type="table">Table 1</ref> (more details including the comparison between fitting curves and experimental spectra are provided in <ref type="figure">Supplementary Fig. 7</ref> ).</s>
          <s>For example, in the RSF of Pt/CNT, the radial peak (C) at 2.75 Å accounts for the X-ray interference with metallic Pt-Pt bond of a coordination number (CN) of 6.45.</s>
          <s>In the RSF of Pd@Pt/CNT sample, it is clear that the main radial peak (1.9-3.1 Å) is split into peaks D and E, as illustrated in <ref target="#fig_1" type="figure">Fig. 2b</ref> , featuring an interference between photoelectrons and both homo-atomic Pt-Pt (at a distance (R Pt-Pt ) of 2.705 Å and a CN (CN Pt-Pt ) of 4.49) and hetero-atomic Pt-Pd (R Pt-Pd = 2.662 Å and CN Pt-Pd = 1.46) bond pairs in the Pt-decorated Pd nanoparticles <ref target="#b27" type="bibr">28</ref> .</s>
          <s>The radial peak with a bond length of 1.893 Å represented the oxygen chemisorption bond in Pt atoms.</s>
          <s>According to a low CN Pt-O (0.57) and a substantially smaller total CN of Pt atoms (CN total_Pt = 5.95) than that of surface atoms in an ideal crystal (CN total_surface = 6-9 at different facets), it can be revealed that the Pt clusters were intercalated in the top layer of the Pd crystal in the Pd@Pt/CNT catalysts.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>As for the result of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT nanocatalyst (see the green line), radial peaks across 1.7-3.2</s>
          <s>Å were attributed to Pt-Co (R Pt-Co = 2.629 Å, CN Pt-Co = 1.37),</s>
          <s>Pt-Pd (R Pt-Pd = 2.671 Å, CN Pt-Pd = 1.16), and Pt-Pt (R Pt-Pt = 2.691 Å, CN Pt-Pt = 1.95) bond pairs.</s>
          <s>Particularly, the CN of Pt-Pt bonds is revealed as 1.95, much smaller than that in the Pd@Pt structure.</s>
          <s>This evidence demonstrates the formation of Pt 3 (possessing an average CN of 2.0 theoretically) on the Co@Pd nanoparticle surface in the as-synthesized ternary catalyst.</s>
          <s>Although the Pt decorations look like nanometer-range clusters in our STEM observation (see <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Fig. 1a</ref> ), they are actually the agglomerated Pt 3 species, and that is the reason why lattice fringes are not visible in the atomic-scale STEM image.</s>
          <s>Moreover, it is found that the hetero-atomic intermix of Co to Pt atoms (χ Co = 30.6%) is higher than that of Pd to Pt atoms (χ Pd = 25.9%),</s>
          <s>indicating a higher extent of galvanic replacement of Pt 4+ to Co atoms (Pt 4+ + Co 0 core → Pt 0 cluster + Co 2+ ) during the synthesis process.</s>
          <s>Notably, the Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst shows a higher total hetero-atomic intermix (χ Co + χ Pd = 56.5%)</s>
          <s>than that of Pd@Pt/CNT catalysts (χ total = χ Pd = 24.5%),</s>
          <s>demonstrating that the Pt 3 species are sitting at the defective regions between the Co core and the Pd shell of Co@Pd nanoparticles.</s>
          <s>
            <ref target="#fig_1" type="figure">Figure 2c</ref> presents the Pd K-edge XANES spectra of the Co@Pd-Pt/CNT nanocatalyst and the control samples (Pd/CNT, Co@Pd/CNT, and Pd@Pt/CNT).</s>
          <s>It is clear that the binary and ternary catalysts are all showing identical positions of inflection point (I), two resolved peaks (A and B), and valley (V) to those of Pd/CNT, demonstrating the metallic state of Pd atoms in these samples <ref target="#b28" type="bibr">29</ref> .</s>
          <s>Particularly, as shown in the enlarged inset, the Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst (the green line) represents the lowest intensities of both peaks A and B, reflecting its lowest empty state in Pd 4s/4p orbital, which is attributed to the steric coverage of Pt 3 species at the defect sites of Pd shell (near the Co core).</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Moreover, <ref target="#fig_1" type="figure">Fig. 2d</ref> presents the k 2 -weighted RSF pattern of Pd K-edge of these four samples, and the fitting curves with experimental EXANES spectra are provided in <ref type="figure">Supplementary Fig. 8</ref> .</s>
          <s>Similar to the analysis of Pt L 3 -edge, the radial peak C in <ref target="#fig_1" type="figure">Fig. 2d</ref> is corresponding to an interference between X-ray and metallic Pd-Pd bond pairs, while the peak D is a typical out-ofphase X-ray interference of bond pairs between heavy transition metal atoms.</s>
          <s>Taking the Pd/CNT as a reference, the Co@Pd structure shows a decreasing intensity of peak C, confirming the unconformable structure of Pd on the Co surface.</s>
          <s>However, while the Pt 3 species are decorated on the Co@Pd surface, the intensity of peak C of Co@Pd-Pt was enhanced, close to that of metal Pd (Pd/CNT).</s>
          <s>This result indicates that Pd shell (on the Co core) tends to form a locally ordered structure with the decoration of Pt 3 , although it exhibits an unconformable characteristic within a long range, as we observed in the STEM images.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Combining the above XAS analysis of both Pt L 3 -edge and Pd K-edge, it is notable that the Pt-Pt bond and Pd-Pd bond of Co@Pd-Pt structure were compressed and elongated at the greatest extent, respectively (see the parameters in <ref target="#tab_0" type="table">Table 1</ref> ).</s>
          <s>Such obvious strain effect is likely to introduce charge relocation, and may affect the catalytic performance accordingly.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Ultraviolet photoelectron spectroscopy.</s>
          <s>Ultraviolet photoelectron spectroscopy (UPS) was carried out to determine the work function (φ) to elucidate the charge localization of the Co@Pd-Pt/ CNT nanocatalyst.</s>
          <s>Work function refers to the energy that is required to remove a valance electron to infinity from a material surface of a given solid, and is a qualitative index to describe the activity of materials in a redox reaction.</s>
          <s>In general, φ of metallic nanoparticles is always dominated by two factors: particle size and surface configuration <ref target="#b29" type="bibr">30,</ref>
            <ref target="#b30" type="bibr">31</ref> .</s>
          <s>Here, <ref target="#fig_2" type="figure">Fig. 3</ref> compares the UPS spectra of various catalyst samples, and φ is determined by the position of secondary cutoff potential.</s>
          <s>Accordingly, the work function follows a trend of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT (4.51 eV) &lt; Pt/CNT (4.74 eV) &lt; Pd@Pt/CNT (4.77 eV) &lt; Co@Pd/CNT (5.01 eV) &lt; Pd/ CNT (5.23 eV).</s>
          <s>Based on our STEM statistic observation (see <ref type="table">Supplementary Table 2)</ref> , it is revealed that the average size of Pd@Pt, Co@Pd, and Co@Pd-Pt nanoparticles are quite similar, within the range of 4.12-4.65 nm.</s>
          <s>However, the Co@Pd-Pt nanoparticles show a much lower work function than those two core-shell structures, indicating a unique surface effect from the Pt 3 decoration.</s>
          <s>Also, a strong charge localization on the Co@Pd-Pt surface was confirmed according to the substantially enhanced intensity (H φ ) of the peak M in the near-Fermi level <ref target="#fig_2" type="figure">(Fig. 3)</ref> , highlighting the quantum size effect of decorated Pt 3 species <ref target="#b31" type="bibr">32</ref> .</s>
          <s>This finding is consistent with our XAS result showing a high rate of 5d 5/2 occupancy of the Pt atoms in Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst.</s>
          <s>CNT carbon nanotube χ represents a hetero-atomic intermix of coordination neighbors to the target atom in a selected bond pair.</s>
          <s>For the Pt L3-edge result, χM = (CNPt-M / CNPt-total) × 100%, where M represents neighboring atoms of Pt and CNPt-total = Σ CNPt-M (for instance, CNPt-total = CNPt-Pt + CNPt-Pd for the sample of Pd@Pt catalyst) R-factor is 0.04 for Co@Pd-Pt, 0.01 for Pd@Pt, 0.01 for Pt/CNT at Pt L3-edge; 0.02 for Co@Pd-Pt, 0.01 for Pd@Pt,; and 0.01 for Pd/CNT at Pd K-edge These experimental evidences are further supported by our density functional theory (DFT) calculations.</s>
          <s>In order to mimic the structure and configuration of Co@Pd-Pt nanoparticles as revealed from our AC-STEM, XAS and additional X-ray diffraction (see <ref type="figure">Supplementary Fig. 9</ref> and <ref type="table">Supplementary Table 3</ref> ) results, a model of five layers of 4 × 4 Co (111) slab capping by one layer of Pt 3 -doped Pd slab was constructed (more details are provided in the calculation part of Methods).</s>
          <s>As a result, a strong electron coupling effect was revealed by the presence of a localized charge bridging the Pt and Co atoms, as illustrated in <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Supplementary Fig. 10</ref> , in agreement with the enhanced H φ of Co@Pd-Pt nanocatalyst in the UPS result.</s>
          <s>A strong negative field is formed around the Pt 3 decoration, and may weaken the adsorption of O 2 /O at the Pt 3 site, thus facilitating the ORR.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Electrochemical testing.</s>
          <s>To assess the ORR catalytic performance of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT nanocatalyst, linear sweep voltammetry (LSV) and cyclic voltammetry (CV) were carried out.</s>
          <s>ORR polarization curves of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT nanocatalysts and various control samples are provided in <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Supplementary Fig. 11</ref> .</s>
          <s>Electrochemical active surface areas (ECSAs) are calculated based on corresponding CV curves by using the oxygen desorption peak in the backward potential sweeping curve (detailed ECSA data of various ORR catalysts are listed in <ref target="#fig_3" type="figure">Supplementary Table 4)</ref> .</s>
          <s>
            <ref target="#fig_3" type="figure">Figure 4a</ref> shows a comparison of ORR polarization curves of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT and commercial Pt/C catalyst (J.M. Pt), which were normalized by the area of carbon electrode.</s>
          <s>At the initial state (see the solid lines), Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst shows an enhanced half-wave potential (E 1/2 ) to the commercial Pt/C, indicating a smaller energy barrier for the ORR.</s>
          <s>The onset potential (E oc ) of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT nanocatalyst is 0.944 V vs. a reversible hydrogen electrode (vs.</s>
          <s>RHE), a little bit lower than that of commercial Pt/C (0.956 V vs. RHE), because of the oxide species on its surface (see the following CV analysis).</s>
          <s>In order to compare the activity for these two catalysts, current densities at 0.85 V vs. RHE (denoted as J k ) are normalized with respect to the loading amount of metal Pt.</s>
          <s>As illustrated in <ref target="#fig_3" type="figure">Fig. 4e,</ref>
            <ref type="table">Table 5</ref> ).</s>
        </p>
        <note type="other">Supplementary Note 3, and more ORR mass activity results of the control samples are provided in Supplementary</note>
        <p>
          <s>The long-term durability of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst was first evaluated by conducting the accelerated degradation test (ADT) up to 310,000 cycles (more detailed ADT conditions can be found in Methods).</s>
          <s>As shown in the representative ORR curves at selected ADT cycles in <ref target="#fig_3" type="figure">Fig. 4b</ref> , the ORR performance were largely retained with no degradation, even after 310k ADT cycles.</s>
          <s>For example, both E oc and E 1/2 show a slight increase during the ADT cycling <ref target="#fig_3" type="figure">(Fig. 4c)</ref> , indicating the additional gain of the active sites; J k was always within a range of 5.0-5.3</s>
          <s>mA cm −2 , showing no obvious deterioration as compared to the initial state <ref target="#fig_3" type="figure">(Fig. 4d)</ref> .</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>For a direct comparison, the final state of ORR curves of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst (#310k cycle) and commercial Pt/C catalyst (#31k cycle, since J k was &lt;75% of the initial state) are plotted in <ref target="#fig_3" type="figure">Fig. 4a</ref> .</s>
          <s>Clearly, the commercial Pt/C catalyst exhibits a negative shift (−32.2 mV vs. RHE) of the half-wave potential after 31k cycles, denoting a degradation of its ORR performance due to the particle agglomeration <ref target="#b24" type="bibr">25</ref> .</s>
          <s>However, in contrast, our Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst shows a positive shift (+27.1 mV vs. RHE) of the half-wave potential after continuous 310k ADT cycles, demonstrating an outstanding durability, and even an enhancement of its ORR performance.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>In addition, <ref target="#fig_3" type="figure">Fig. 4e</ref> summarizes the change of mass activity of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst during ADT cycling, and the commercial Pt/C is used as a baseline catalyst for comparison.</s>
          <s>The mass activity of the commercial Pt/C degraded steadily by 30% after 31k cycles, due to the agglomeration of Pt nanoparticles (see our TEM result in <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Supplementary Fig. 12</ref> ).</s>
          <s>However, it is surprising to find that the mass activity of the Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst always maintained at a very high level, as illustrated in <ref target="#fig_3" type="figure">Fig. 4e</ref> .</s>
          <s>Notably, the mass activity was still as high as 2103.6 mA mg Pt −1 at 0.85 V vs. RHE after the #310k ADT cycle, suggesting this is not the limit of the Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Discussion</head>
        <p>
          <s>The Pt 3 -decorated Co@Pd catalyst shows desirable ORR activity and durability simultaneously, as compared to the advanced Pt-decorated metal catalysts in alkaline media from the literature <ref target="#b32" type="bibr">[33]</ref>
            <ref target="#b33" type="bibr">[34]</ref>
            <ref target="#b34" type="bibr">[35]</ref>
            <ref target="#b35" type="bibr">[36]</ref> , in which the highest mass activity is at a level of about 400 mA mg Pt −1 at 0.85 V vs. RHE and the degradation always takes place around 5k cycles (more detailed comparisons are summarized in <ref type="table">Supplementary Table 6</ref> ).</s>
          <s>Clearly, in contrast to the Pt overlayers and large Pt clusters on metal nanoparticles <ref target="#b32" type="bibr">[33]</ref>
            <ref target="#b33" type="bibr">[34]</ref>
            <ref target="#b34" type="bibr">[35]</ref>
            <ref target="#b35" type="bibr">[36]</ref> , the atomic-scale Pt decoration <ref target="#b25" type="bibr">26</ref> on Co@Pd nanoparticle not only shows a unique surface configuration at a higher Pt utilization efficiency, but also provides a further improved promotion effect toward ORR.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>To have a better understanding of the specific advantages from the Pt <ref target="#b2" type="bibr">3</ref> decoration, we first analyze the CV curves of the Co@Pd-Pt catalyst that were collected during the ADT cycling, as shown in <ref target="#fig_3" type="figure">Fig. 4f</ref> (more detailed CV curves at every 10,000 of the first 70,000 cycles are provided in <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Supplementary Fig. 13</ref> ).</s>
          <s>At the initial state (the red solid line), current peaks corresponding to the redox of the metal nanoparticle surface can be revealed: for example, the five current peaks (B 1 -B 5 ), as marked in the forward sweeping curve, are attributed to the formation of oxide species with different combinations of Co, Pd, and Pt, while the obvious peak C in the backward sweeping is determined as reduction of PdO, according to the literature <ref target="#b36" type="bibr">37,</ref>
            <ref target="#b37" type="bibr">38</ref> as well as our CV results of control samples and theoretical calculation (more details are expanded in Supplementary Note 4 on the basis of Supplementary <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Fig. 14 and Supplementary Tables 7 and 8</ref> ).</s>
          <s>As the ADT going on, an obvious evolution of the oxide reduction peak C is found during the first 50k cycles: the peak intensity was decreasing while the peak position was gradually shifting to the high potential region, reflecting a catalyst surface reconstruction.</s>
          <s>Meanwhile, the redox peaks at hydrogen underpotential deposition (H upd ) region, as indicated by A 1 and A 1 * in <ref target="#fig_3" type="figure">Fig. 4f</ref> , were becoming narrow and sharp at the position of~0.1 V vs. RHE, showing a unique hydrogen adsorption/desorption characteristic of the Co@Pd-Pt catalyst.</s>
          <s>According to the published results in literature, this kind of strong H 2 evolution activity is a typical feature of sub-nanometer Pt clusters <ref target="#b38" type="bibr">[39]</ref>
            <ref target="#b39" type="bibr">[40]</ref>
            <ref target="#b40" type="bibr">[41]</ref> , consistent with the decorated Pt 3 species on the Co@Pd surface.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Then, between the interval from #50k to #60k cycles, the oxide reduction peak C continued to shift to the high potential region, but the intensity was greatly enhanced at #60k ADT cycles, as denoted by peak D, which can be determined as reduction of PtO <ref target="#b36" type="bibr">37,</ref>
            <ref target="#b37" type="bibr">38</ref> .</s>
          <s>In view of the gradually enhanced peaks A 1 and A 1 * , it can be concluded that the oxygen reduction activity at the catalyst surface was dominated by Pt phase at that time, instead of the initial Pd phase.</s>
          <s>Afterwards, the shape of CV curves was relatively stable during the subsequent ADT cycles (from #60k to #310k) and the peak intensities of A 1 and A 1 * were continuously</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Commercial Pt/C, initial</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Commercial Pt/C, # 31k</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Co@Pd-Pt/CNT, initial</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Co@Pd-Pt/CNT, # 310k</s>
        </p>
        <formula xml:id="formula_0">0.85 V J k J k E oc E 1/2</formula>
        <p>
          <s>Current density (mA cm becoming stronger, demonstrating that the sub-nanometer Pt decoration still survived with a further increment of their surface area.</s>
          <s>For a direct visualization of the survival of the Pt decoration, atomic-scale STEM characterization was carried out on the post-ADT Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst that was collected after 310,000 ADT cycles.</s>
          <s>As a comparison, <ref target="#fig_4" type="figure">Fig. 5</ref> presents the atomic-scale HAADF-STEM images of the as-prepared Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst <ref target="#fig_4" type="figure">(Fig. 5a</ref> ) and the post-ADT one <ref target="#fig_4" type="figure">(Fig. 5b)</ref> .</s>
          <s>Obviously, the distribution of Pt 3 species was changing during the ADT cycling, validating the proposed surface reconstruction: the initially agglomerated Pt 3 species (as indicated by yellow arrows in <ref target="#fig_4" type="figure">Fig. 5a</ref> ) dispersed into isolated atomic-scale Pt species on the Co@Pd nanoparticle surface.</s>
          <s>Particularly, the predominant Pt species in the post-ADT sample were revealed as isolated Pt 3 , which can be directly observed in <ref target="#fig_4" type="figure">Fig. 5b</ref> (as highlighted by yellow circles), while some Pt single atoms (Pt 1 ) were also found (as marked by red circles).</s>
          <s>Quantitative analysis regarding the size of Pt 3 species are expanded in Supplementary Note 5. Based on STEM data with higher statistics (e.g., see <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Supplementary Fig. 15</ref> ), the density of Pt 3 in the post-ADT catalyst is estimated to be as high as 4.6 Pt 3 /100 nm 2 , indicating that majority of Pt 3 decoration survived on the Co@Pd nanoparticle surface after over 300,000 ADT cycles.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Actually, the defective region between the Co core and the unconformable Pt shell plays an important role in dispersing the Pt 3 species.</s>
          <s>As revealed through the STEM and XAS results, decorated Pt 3 species prefer to sit at the defective regions between the Co core and the Pt shell.</s>
          <s>Therefore, since considerable amount of defect sites are generated on the Co@Pd surface during ORR due to decomposition of Pd/Co oxides and desorption of oxygen species, the Pt 3 species tend to relocate at the new defective sites to minimize the surface energy.</s>
          <s>This behavior is the origin for enhancement of ORR activity that was observed in the Co@Pd-Pt catalyst during the continuous potential sweeping.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>For a further exploration of the stability of the Pt 3 species on the Co@Pd surface, we stored the rotation electrode (after 310,000 ADT cycles) in distilled water for a couple of days to restore its pH value, and then continued the electrochemical testing for additional 12,000 ADT cycles; therefore, 322k cycles in total.</s>
          <s>Consequently, the Co@Pd-Pt catalyst was still highly active, representing a stable mass activity (&gt;2000mAmg Pt −1 at 0.85 V vs. RHE) after #322k ADT cycle, as compared to the state before storage.</s>
          <s>This result further highlights the outstanding durability of the Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst, which is promising in practical and commercial applications of alkaline fuel cells.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>According to our experimental evidence, it is confirmed that the decorated Pt 3 species are stable and dominate the surface oxygen redox of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst.</s>
          <s>Going a step further for deeper mechanistic insights, DFT calculation revealed the ORR promotion effect of the Pt 3 decoration on the Co@Pd surface (more calculation details are provided in Methods).</s>
          <s>As shown by the result in <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Supplementary Fig. 10</ref> , both the charge localization around Pt 3 and the electron-coupling effect between Pt and Co atoms are revealed, thus high density of electrons were extracted in the near-Fermi level.</s>
          <s>Hence, a strong negative electric field is induced and weakens the adsorption of O/O 2 at the Pt 3 and its neighboring sites.</s>
          <s>Furthermore, we calculated the oxygen adsorption energy (E O ads ) on the surface of Co@Pd-Pt catalyst as well as Pt <ref type="formula">(111)</ref> and Pd (111) surfaces, and the result is illustrated in <ref target="#fig_6" type="figure">Fig. 6</ref> .</s>
          <s>Accordingly, it is clear that E ads O peaks and E ads O valleys are distributed periodically in the contours of Pt (111) and Pd (111) surfaces.</s>
          <s>However, the presence of slight gradient of E O ads is found on the Co@Pd-Pt surface, indicating feasible relocation pathways for the O ads between O 2 splitting sites (site S) and O reduction sites (site V).</s>
          <s>Meanwhile, relocation of O ads to the neighboring sites reduces the possibility of passivation on Pt 3 by intermediates (e.g., the suppressed electric double layer current in the CV curves).</s>
          <s>This characteristic enables the neighboring sites to share the loading from the Pt 3 in subsequent reaction steps, and maintain the high ORR activity of the Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Furthermore, it is found that the adsorption energy for O 2 molecule (E ads O2 ) is very close to 0 on most surface sites of Co@Pd-Pt (see the data in <ref target="#tab_0" type="table">Supplementary Tables 9 and 10</ref> ).</s>
          <s>This characteristic implies a substantially weakened O 2 adsorption on the Co@Pd-Pt surface, which exhibits an oxidation resistance, as compared to the Pt (111) or the Pd (111) surface, thus improving the durability of the Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst.</s>
          <s>Notably, the theoretical findings that the Pt 3 decoration not only reduces the Pt loading, but also provides a unique charge localization state that greatly improves the ORR performance.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>In conclusion, we designed and synthesized a ternary nanocatalyst with low Pt-loading that consists of a Co@Pd core-shell structure and surface decoration of Pt 3 species to catalyze ORR in alkaline electrolytes.</s>
          <s>Advanced characterization result and theoretical calculation revealed a unique charge localization induced by the Pt 3 decoration at the interfacial region between Co core A As-prepared s-prepared As-prepared Post-ADT ost-ADT Post-ADT a b and Pd shell.</s>
          <s>Accordingly, the Co@Pd-Pt catalyst shows an ORR mass activity improved by a factor of 30.6 relative to a commercial Pt catalyst.</s>
          <s>In particular, this ternary catalyst exhibits an outstanding durability, maintaining the high activity, without degradation, for more than 322,000 potential cycles in alkaline electrolytes, due to the decorated Pt 3 species that becomes dispersed and stabilized on the Co@Pd surface under working condition.</s>
          <s>The Co@Pd-Pt catalyst, possessing desirable catalytic activity and durability simultaneously with a low Pt content, is promising for the future development of low-cost, high-performance alkaline fuel cells.</s>
          <s>Of course, the strategy to decorate atomic-level Pt species on the defective regions of the metals is not limited to the Co-Pd-Pt system, and can be extended further and make applicable to the other catalyst systems with most types of 3d transition metals in the core region.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Methods</head>
        <p>
          <s>Catalyst synthesis.</s>
          <s>Pt 3 decorated Co-Pd core-shell nanocatalysts were synthesized by a wet chemical reduction method with sequential control.</s>
          <s>To improve the attachment, CNT support (CNT, Cnano Technology Ltd.) was acid treated in aqueous solution of 4.0 M sulfuric acid at 80°C for 4 h (corresponding characterization result is presented in <ref target="#fig_0" type="figure">Supplementary Fig. 16</ref> ).</s>
          <s>The CNT powders were filtered and then washed with distilled water until the pH value of the washing liquid reached 6.0.</s>
          <s>After washing and drying, the resulting 36 mg of CNT powder was immersed in an aqueous solution of cobalt chloride (CoCl <ref target="#b1" type="bibr">2</ref> Synthesis of Co@Pd/CNT nanocatalysts followed similar processes as those used for the preparation Co@Pd-Pt/CNT nanocatalyst, except for the Pt decoration treatment.</s>
          <s>Co@Pt/CNT and Pd@Pt/CNT nanocatalysts were synthesized by immersing CNT in Co and Pd precursor aqueous solution at 25°C for 4 h, respectively, followed by the addition of 3.0 g of NaBH <ref target="#b3" type="bibr">4</ref> , and then 500 mg of Pt precursor solution to the reaction system.</s>
          <s>More details of sample preparation are provided in Supplementary Information.</s>
          <s>Structure characterization.</s>
          <s id="0" type="Image:Microscopy">TEM was performed on a JEOL Grand ARM equipped with two spherical aberration correctors at 300 kV.</s>
          <s id="1" type="Image">HAADF-STEM images were recorded using a convergence semi-angle of 22mrad, and inner and outer collection angles of 83 and 165mrad, respectively.</s>
          <s>XAS, XPS, and UPS experiments were carried out at beamlines BL-17C, 01C1, and BL-24A1 of the National Synchrotron Radiation Research Center (NSRRC, Taiwan).</s>
          <s>XRD patterns were measured at beamline BL-12B2 of Spring-8, Japan.</s>
          <s>Model analysis was conducted in the Artemis program with atomic structural models determined in physical structure characterization, and models for data analysis were generated by feff8.0</s>
          <s>code.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>Electrochemical testing.</s>
          <s>As-synthesized nanocatalysts were mixed in a slurry sample and coated on a rotational disk electrode to conduct LSV and CV analyses.</s>
          <s>The slurry samples were made of 5.0 mg active carbon-supported nanocatalysts mixed in distilled water (14.0 mL), IPA (6.0 mL), and 5 wt% Nafion (0.1 mL).</s>
          <s>The mixture was stirred at 250 rpm for 30 min prior to ultrasonication at 30°C for 30 min.</s>
          <s>To prepare the working electrode in the ORR sweeping experiment, the slurry (20.0μL) was dropped and dried on top of a rotating graphite electrode (with a diameter of 5.0 mm).</s>
          <s id="2" type="Tabular data">LSV data were collected using a potentiostat (CH Instruments Model 600B) equipped with a three-electrode electrochemical system.</s>
          <s>This system consisted of a standard electrode of mercury oxide electrode (the voltage was calibrated by 0.098 V in alignment to that of RHE), a counter electrode of Pt metal wire, and a working electrode.</s>
          <s>The electrolyte was an aqueous solution of KOH (0.1 M).</s>
          <s>The voltage scan rate was 5 mV s −1 for LSV and 50 mV s −1 for the accelerated degradation test.</s>
          <s>In these tests, the speed of the rotation electrode was 1600rpm.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>First principle calculation.</s>
          <s>Calculations based on DFT were carried out with the Vienna Ab-initio Simulation Package <ref target="#b41" type="bibr">[42]</ref>
            <ref target="#b42" type="bibr">[43]</ref>
            <ref target="#b43" type="bibr">[44]</ref>
            <ref target="#b44" type="bibr">[45]</ref> .</s>
          <s>All the calculations were performed using a plane-wave basis with a cutoff kinetic energy of 420 eV and the projector augmented wave method <ref target="#b45" type="bibr">46,</ref>
            <ref target="#b46" type="bibr">47</ref> .</s>
          <s>The exchange-correlation functional was treated at the level of the generalized gradient approximations, using the Perdew-Burke-Ernzerhof functional <ref target="#b47" type="bibr">48</ref> .</s>
          <s>The structure of Co@Pd-Pt catalyst was modeled by a five layer of 4 × 4 Co (111) slab capping by one layer of Pd doped with Pt 3 (Co5L-Pd1L-Pt 3 ), which represents the structure of Co@Pd-Pt based on our experimental evidence, particularly, taking the neighboring Co and Pd atoms around Pt 3 into account.</s>
          <s>It is worthwhile noting that the (111) slab in face-centered cubic phase is used to keep consistent with the observation from the XRD result (see <ref type="figure">Supplementary Fig. 9</ref> ) showing the preferential growth of the (111) facet in the Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalyst.</s>
          <s>For comparison, the models of three Pt atoms incorporating into six layers of Pd (111) and three Pt atoms incorporating into six layers of Co(111) were also constructed, respectively.</s>
          <s>In the calculation part, the Pt atoms were positioned at different sorption sites of the top layer to confirm the most stable atomic configuration.</s>
          <s>We applied 5 × 5 × 1 Γ-centered k-points to map the Brillouin zone and an inter-slab vacuum spacing of 15 Å to avoid the interaction between the replicas of the slabs.</s>
          <s>The sensitivity of total energies for slab thickness, vacuum spacing, and kinetic energy cutoff were examined as well.</s>
          <s>All the relevant adsorbates and the upper most four layers of slabs were fully relaxed, while the bottom two layers were fixed to their calculated bulk position.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
          <s>To investigate the electron localization of Co@Pd-Pt catalyst quantitatively, we introduced the charge density difference distribution (Δρ), which is defined as Δρ = ρ T − ρ S − ρ Pt .</s>
          <s>Here, ρ T is the charge density of Co 5 LPd 1 L(111)-Pt 3 model, ρ S is the charge density of Co 5 LPd 1 L(111) without Pt 3 decoration, and ρ Pt is the charge density of isolated Pt 3 at the same position in the model.</s>
          <s>The adsorption energy (E ads ) of a single oxygen atom adsorbed on the surfaces of interest is defined as E ads = E(O − NC) − 1/2E(O 2 ) − E(NC), where E(O − NC) is the total energy of the entire system, E(O 2 ) is the energy of an oxygen molecule, and E(NC) is the energy of the pristine slab.</s>
          <s>The negative values of E ads refer to the oxygen adsorption in endothermic.</s>
        </p>
      </div>
      <figure xml:id="fig_0">
        <head>Fig. 1</head>
        <label>1</label>
        <figDesc>Fig. 1 Scanning transmission electron microscopy (STEM) of Pt-decorated Co-Pd. a Atomic-scale high angle annular dark field-STEM (HAADF-STEM) image of as-prepared Pt-decorated Co-Pd (Co@Pd-Pt) nanocatalyst. Yellow and red arrows indicate the decorated Pt species and the unconformable Pd shell regions, respectively. Scale bar: 1 nm. b-d EDS elemental maps of the Co@Pd-Pt nanocatalyst in a</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure xml:id="fig_1">
        <head>Fig. 2</head>
        <label>2</label>
        <figDesc>Fig. 2 X-ray absorption spectra of Pt-decorated Co-Pd and control samples. a X-ray absorption near-edge spectra (XANES) of Pt L 3 -edge of standard Pt foil, Pt/carbon nanotube (CNT), Pd-Pt core-shell/CNT (Pd@Pt/CNT), and Pt-decorated Co-Pd/CNT (Co@Pd-Pt/CNT) catalysts. The inset shows the enlarged post-edge region. b Fourier-transformed extended X-ray absorption fine structure (FT-EXAFS) of the four samples in a. c XANES spectra of Pd K-edge of Pd/CNT, Pd@Pt/CNT, Co-Pd core-shell/CNT (Co@Pd/CNT), and Co@Pd-Pt/CNT catalysts. The inset shows the enlarged region of peaks A and B. d FT-EXAFS of the four samples in c</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure xml:id="fig_2">
        <head>Fig. 3</head>
        <label>3</label>
        <figDesc>Fig. 3 Ultraviolet photoelectron spectra of Pt-decorated Co-Pd and controls. The work function of Pt-decorated Co-Pd (Co@Pd-Pt/carbon nanotube (CNT)) catalyst is lower than that of the control samples including Pt/CNT, Pd/CNT, Pd-Pt core-shell (Pd@Pt/CNT), and Co-Pd core-shell (Co@Pd/ CNT) catalysts</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure xml:id="fig_3">
        <head>Fig. 4</head>
        <label>4</label>
        <figDesc>Fig. 4 Electrochemical results of Pt-decorated Co-Pd nanocatalyst. a Initial and final oxygen reduction reaction (ORR) polarization curves of commercial Pt/ C and Pt-decorated Co-Pd (Co@Pd-Pt/carbon nanotube (CNT)) catalysts. b ORR polarization curves of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT at selected accelerated degradation test (ADT) cycles. c Changes of onset potential and half-wave potential of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT at selective ADT cycles. d Changes of kinetic current density of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT at selective ADT cycles. e Comparison of ORR mass activity of commercial Pt/C and Co@Pd-Pt/CNT at selected ADT cycles. f Cyclic voltammetry (CV) curves of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT at selected ADT cycles</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure xml:id="fig_4">
        <head>Fig. 5</head>
        <label>5</label>
        <figDesc>Fig. 5 Dispersion of Pt trimer species on the Co-Pd surface. a High angle annular dark field-scanning transmission electron microscopy (HAADF-STEM) image of the as-prepared Pt-decorated Co-Pd (Co@Pd-Pt) catalyst. Yellow arrows indicate the agglomerated Pt trimer species. Scale bar: 2 nm. b HAADF-STEM image of the Co@Pd-Pt catalyst after 310,000 accelerated degradation test (ADT) cycles. Yellow and red circles indicate the dispersed Pt trimer species and single Pt atoms, respectively. Scale bar: 2 nm</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure xml:id="fig_5">
        <head/>
        <label/>
        <figDesc>, 99%, MW = 129.84, Sigma-Aldrich Co.) and stirred at 250 rpm at 25°C for 4 h. This solution (solution A) contained 33.0 mg CoCl 2 (0.25mmol of Co metal ion) and 6.0 g H 2 O. After immersion, 3.0 g of H 2 O solution containing 20.0 mg (0.54 mmol) NaBH 4 (99%, Sigma-Aldrich Co.) was added to solution A and stirred at 250 rpm for 10 s. Then, Pd precursor solution comprising 2.0 g distilled water and~48.4 mg (~0.046 mmol) Pd ion was added in solution A to form solution B. In solution B, the mole ratio of Co/Pd was 1.0. The Pd precursor solution was prepared by dissolving metal powders (Pd, 99%, Sigma-Aldrich Co.) in 1.0 M HCl (aq) . After 20 s, 500 mg of aqueous solution containing~26.6 mg H 2 PtCl 6 •6H 2 O (99%, Sigma-Aldrich Co.) was added to solution B within a reaction time of 10 s (the atomic ratio of Pt/Pd is 1/20). In this step, Pt 4+ was adsorbed on defect sites of the Pd shell and Co-Pd interface, and then reduced to Pt 3 by interacting with H.</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure xml:id="fig_6">
        <head>Fig. 6</head>
        <label>6</label>
        <figDesc>Fig. 6 Contours of oxygen adsorption energy. E ads O in models of Pt (111), Pd (111), and Pt-decorated Co-Pd catalyst surface. Atomic structures of the topmost layers are shown in schematics in which blue and yellow spheres correspond to Pd and Pt atoms, respectively. Co atoms are not shown in the Ptdecorated Co-Pd (Co@Pd-Pt) model</figDesc>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="true" xml:id="tab_0">
        <head>Table 1</head>
        <label>1</label>
        <figDesc>Quantitative results of X-ray absorption spectroscopy model analysis at Pt L 3 -edge and Pd K-edge of Co@Pd-Pt/CNT nanocatalysts and control samples</figDesc>
        <table>Sample 
Pt L 3 -edge 
Pd K-edge 

Bond pair 
CN 
R 
χ 
Bond pair 
CN 
R 
χ 

Co@Pd-Pt 
Pt-Pt 
1.95 
2.691 
43.5% 
Pd-Pd 
5.88 
2.762 
62.3% 
Pt-Pd 
1.16 
2.671 
25.9% 
Pd-Pt 
2.91 
2.711 
30.8% 
Pt-Co 
1.37 
2.629 
30.6% 
Pd-Co 
0.65 
2.708 
6.9% 
Co@Pd 
Pd-Pd 
5.51 
2.731 
89.9% 
Pd-Co 
0.62 
2.753 
10.1% 
Pt-O 
0.57 
1.893 
Pd-Pd 
5.5 
2.75 
66.7% 
Pd@Pt 
Pt-Pt 
4.49 
2.705 
75.5% 
Pd-Pt 
2.75 
2.723 
33.3% 
Pt-Pd 
1.46 
2.662 
24.5% 
Pd-O 
0.47 
2.03 
Pt/CNT 
Pt-Pt 
6.45 
2.752 
Pd/CNT 
Pd-Pd 
5.71 
2.747 
Pd-O 
0.78 
2.041 

</table>
      </figure>
      <figure type="table" validated="false" xml:id="tab_1">
        <head/>
        <label/>
        <figDesc>4% (detailed calculation of mass activity can be found in</figDesc>
        <table>the Co@Pd-
Pt/CNT catalyst exhibits an initial mass activity of 2055.1 mA 
mg Pt 
−1 at 0.85 V vs. RHE, representing an improvement by 
a factor of 30.6 relative to the commercial Pt/C catalyst 
(67.1 mAmg Pt 
−1 at 0.85 V vs. RHE), while at a low Pt loading 
of 2.</table>
      </figure>
      <note place="foot">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-019-08323-w</note>
      <note place="foot">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | (2019) 10:440 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-019-08323-w | www.nature.com/naturecommunications</note>
      <note place="foot">© The Author(s) 2019</note>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="acknowledgement">
        <div>
          <head>Acknowledgements</head>
          <p>
            <s>This work was supported by the Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan (MOST 106-2112-M-007-016-MY3 and MOST 105-3113-E-006-019-CC2) and the National Science Foundation (grant numbers DMR-1506535 and CBET-1159240).</s>
            <s>We would like to acknowledge the help from the National Synchrotron Radiation Research Center (NSRRC), Hsinchu, Taiwan, for various synchrotron-based measurements.</s>
            <s>Transmission electron microscopy was carried out at the Irvine Materials Research Institute (IMRI), University of California, Irvine.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="annex">
        <div>
          <head>Data availability</head>
          <p>
            <s>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Additional information</head>
          <p>
            <s>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-019-08323-w.</s>
          </p>
          <p>
            <s>Competing interests: The authors declare no competing interests.</s>
          </p>
          <p>
            <s>Reprints and permission information is available online at http://npg.nature.com/</s>
            <s>reprintsandpermissions/ Journal peer review information: Nature Communications thanks Chen-Hao Wang and the other anonymous reviewers for their contribution to the peer review of this work.</s>
          </p>
          <p>
            <s>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</s>
          </p>
          <p>
            <s>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</s>
            <s>The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material.</s>
            <s>If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder.</s>
            <s>To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/ licenses/by/4.0/.</s>
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="references">
        <listBibl>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b0">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Just a dream-or future reality?</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">H</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">A</forename>
                  <surname>Gasteiger</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">N</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">M</forename>
                  <surname>Markovic</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Science</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">324</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="48" to="49" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2009"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b1">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Electrocatalyst approaches and challenges for automotive fuel cells</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">K</forename>
                  <surname>Debe</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Nature</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">486</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="43" to="51" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2012"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b2">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Electrochemistry and the future of the automobile</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">F</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">T</forename>
                  <surname>Wagner</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">B</forename>
                  <surname>Lakshmanan</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">F</forename>
                  <surname>Mathias</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. Lett</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="2204" to="2219" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2010"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b3">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Oxygen electrochemistry as a cornerstone for sustainable energy conversion</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">I</forename>
                  <surname>Katsounaros</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Cherevko</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">R</forename>
                  <surname>Zeradjanin</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">K</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">J J</forename>
                  <surname>Mayrhofer</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Angew. Chem. Int. Ed</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="102" to="121" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2014"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b4">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Platinum-based oxygen reduction electrocatalysts</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Wu</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">H</forename>
                  <surname>Yang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Acc. Chem. Res</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="1848" to="1857" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2013"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b5">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Alloys of platinum and early transition metals as oxygen reduction electrocatalysts</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Greeley</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Nat. Chem</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="552" to="556" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2009"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b6">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Recent advances in electrocatalysts for oxygen reduction reaction</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Shao</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">Q</forename>
                  <surname>Chang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">P</forename>
                  <surname>Dodelet</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <surname>Chenitz</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Chem. Rev</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="3594" to="3657" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2016"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b7">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Effect of surface composition on electronic structure, stability, and electrocatalytic properties of Pt-transition metal alloys: Pt-skin versus Pt-skeleton surfaces</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">V</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">R</forename>
                  <surname>Stamenkovic</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="8813" to="8819" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2006"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b8">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Synthesis and oxygen reduction activity of shape-controlled Pt 3 Ni nanopolyhedra</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Zhang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">H</forename>
                  <surname>Yang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Fang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Zou</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Nano Lett</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="638" to="644" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2010"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b9">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Structurally ordered intermetallic platinum-cobalt core-shell nanoparticles with enhanced activity and stability as oxygen reduction electrocatalysts</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <surname>Wang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Nat. Mater</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="81" to="87" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2013"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b10">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Highly crystalline multimetallic nanoframes with three dimensional electrocatalytic surfaces</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <surname>Chen</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Science</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">343</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="1339" to="1343" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2014"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b11">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">High-performance transition metal-doped Pt 3 Ni octahedra for oxygen reduction reaction</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">X</forename>
                  <surname>Huang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Science</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">348</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="1230" to="1234" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2015"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b12">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Truncated octahedral Pt 3 Ni oxygen reduction reaction electrocatalysts</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Wu</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="4984" to="4985" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2010"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b13">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Synthesis and characterization of 9 nm Pt-Ni octahedra with a record high activity of 3.3 A/mg Pt for the oxygen reduction reaction</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">I</forename>
                  <surname>Choi</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Nano Lett</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="3420" to="3425" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2013"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b14">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Synthesis and characterization of platinum monolayer oxygen-reduction electrocatalysts with Co-Pd core-shell nanoparticle supports</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Shao</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">K</forename>
                  <surname>Sasaki</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">N</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">S</forename>
                  <surname>Marinkovic</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">L</forename>
                  <surname>Zhang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">R</forename>
                  <surname>Adzic</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Electrochem. Commun</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="2848" to="2853" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2007"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b15">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Pt-encapsulated Pd-Co nanoalloy electrocatalysts for oxygen reduction reaction in fuel cells</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <surname>Sarkar</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">V</forename>
                  <surname>Murugan</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <surname>Manthiram</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Langmuir</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="2894" to="2903" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2010"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b16">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Pt-decorated PdCo@Pd/C core-shell nanoparticles with enhanced stability and electrocatalytic activity for the oxygen reduction reaction</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <surname>Wang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="17664" to="17666" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2010"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b17">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Gram-scale-synthesized Pd 2 Co-supported Pt monolayer electrocatalysts for oxygen reduction reaction</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">W</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">P</forename>
                  <surname>Zhou</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. A</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="8950" to="8957" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2010"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b18">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Facile synthesis of carbon-supported Pd-Co core-shell nanoparticles as oxygen reduction electrocatalysts and their enhanced activity and stability with monolayer Pt decoration</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <surname>Wang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="2274" to="2281" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2012"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b19">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Stability issues in Pd-based catalysts: the role of surface Pt in improving the stability and oxygen reduction reaction (ORR) activity</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">K</forename>
                  <surname>Singh</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <surname>Rahul</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Neergat</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="13044" to="13051" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2013"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b20">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Computational and experimental study of the volcano behavior of the oxygen reduction activity of PdM@PdPt/ C (M = Pt, Ni, Co, Fe, and Cr) core-shell electrocatalysts</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">Q</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">T</forename>
                  <surname>Trinh</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Yang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">Y</forename>
                  <surname>Lee</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Saeys</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J. Catal</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">291</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="26" to="35" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2012"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b21">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">High performance platinum single atom electrocatalyst for oxygen reduction reaction</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Liu</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">15938</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2017"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b22">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Solvothermal synthesis of platinum alloy nanoparticles for oxygen reduction electrocatalysis</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">K</forename>
                  <surname>Carpenter</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">T</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">E</forename>
                  <surname>Moylan</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">S</forename>
                  <surname>Kukreja</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">H</forename>
                  <surname>Atwan</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">M</forename>
                  <surname>Tessema</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="8535" to="8542" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2012"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b23">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Compositional segregation in shaped Pt alloy nanoparticles and their structural behaviour during electrocatalysis</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <surname>Cui</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">L</forename>
                  <surname>Gan</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Heggen</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Rudi</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">P</forename>
                  <surname>Strasser</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Nat. Mater</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="765" to="771" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2013"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b24">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Accelerated stress test of Pt/C nanoparticles in an interface with an anion-exchange membrane-an identical-location transmission electron microscopy study</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <surname>Lafforgue</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Chatenet</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">L</forename>
                  <surname>Dubau</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">R</forename>
                  <surname>Dekel</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">ACS Catal</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="1278" to="1286" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2018"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b25">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Atomic scale Pt decoration promises oxygen reduction properties of Co@Pd nanocatalysts in alkaline electrolytes for 310k redox cycles</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">Y</forename>
                  <surname>Zhuang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Sustain. Energy Fuels</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="946" to="957" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2018"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b26">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Visibility of single atoms</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">V</forename>
                  <surname>Crewe</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Wall</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Langmore</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Science</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">168</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="1338" to="1340" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="1970"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b27">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Lithium assisted "dissolution-alloying" synthesis of nanoalloys from individual bulk metals</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">H</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">M</forename>
                  <surname>Barkholtz</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Chem. Mater</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="2267" to="2277" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2016"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b28">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Design of a surface alloy catalyst for steam reforming</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">F</forename>
                  <surname>Besenbacher</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Science</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">279</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="1913" to="1915" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="1998"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b29">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Composition and crystallography dependence of the work function: experiment and calculations of Pt-Al alloys</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">L</forename>
                  <surname>Kornblum</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">P</forename>
                  <surname>Shekhter</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">Y</forename>
                  <surname>Slovatizky</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">Y</forename>
                  <surname>Amouyal</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Eizenberg</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
                <biblScope unit="page">125305</biblScope>
                <date type="published" when="2012"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b30">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Changes in surface morphology and work function caused by corrosion in aluminum alloys</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Xue</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J. Phys. Chem. Solids</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="781" to="787" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2012"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b31">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Photoemission from mass-selected monodispersed Pt clusters</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">W</forename>
                  <surname>Eberhardt</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="780" to="783" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="1990"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b32">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Hydrogenated uniform Pt clusters supported on porous CaMnO 3 as a bifunctional electrocatalyst for enhanced oxygen reduction and evolution</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">X</forename>
                  <surname>Han</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Adv. Mater</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="2047" to="2051" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2014"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b33">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Pt-coated Pd nanocubes as catalysts for alkaline oxygen reduction activity</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <surname>Lee</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <surname>Yang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">C</forename>
                  <surname>Liu</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">Z</forename>
                  <surname>Liu</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Ye</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J. Power Sources</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">268</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="712" to="717" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2014"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b34">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Co@Pt core@shell nanoparticles encapsulated in porous carbon derived from zeolitic imidazolate framework 67 for oxygen electroreduction in alkaline media</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">L</forename>
                  <surname>Wang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J. Power Sources</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">343</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="458" to="466" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2017"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b35">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">One-pot synthesis of Pd@PtNi core-shell nanoflowers supported on the multi-walled carbon nanotubes with boosting activity toward oxygen reduction in alkaline electrolyte</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">S</forename>
                  <surname>Liu</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J. Power Sources</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">365</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="26" to="33" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2017"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b36">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Effect of oxidative heat-treatment on electrochemical properties and oxygen reduction reaction (ORR) activity of Pd-Co alloy catalysts</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <surname>Rahul</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">K</forename>
                  <surname>Singh</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Neergat</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">J. Electroanal. Chem</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">712</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="223" to="229" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2014"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b37">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Investigation on the reduction of the oxides of Pd and graphite in alkaline medium and the simultaneous evolution of oxygen reduction reaction and peroxide generation features</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">K</forename>
                  <surname>Singh</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <surname>Ramesh</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <surname>Devivaraprasad</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">A</forename>
                  <surname>Chakraborty</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Neergat</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Electrochim. Acta</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="81" to="89" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2016"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b38">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Preparation, structure, and stability of Pt and Pd monolayer modified Pd and Pt electrocatalysts</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">P</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">P</forename>
                  <surname>Wells</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="5773" to="5781" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2009"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b39">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Dispersing Pt atoms onto nanoporous gold for high performance direct formic acid fuel cells</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">R</forename>
                  <surname>Wang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Chem. Sci</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="403" to="409" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2014"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b40">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Surface-limited synthesis of Pt nanocluster decorated Pd hierarchical structures with enhanced electrocatalytic activity toward oxygen reduction reaction</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">T</forename>
                  <surname>Yang</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="17162" to="17170" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="2015"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b41">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Ab initio molecular dynamics for liquid metals</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">G</forename>
                  <surname>Kresse</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Hafner</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="558" to="561" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="1993"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b42">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Ab initio molecular-dynamics simulation of the liquidmetal-amorphous-semiconductor transition in germanium</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">G</forename>
                  <surname>Kresse</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Hafner</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="14251" to="14269" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="1994"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b43">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Efficient iterative schemes for ab initio total-energy calculations using a plane-wave basis set</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">G</forename>
                  <surname>Kresse</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Furthmuller</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="11169" to="11186" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="1996"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b44">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Efficiency of ab-initio total energy calculations for metals and semiconductors using a plane-wave basis set</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">G</forename>
                  <surname>Kresse</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <surname>Furthmuller</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Comput. Mater. Sci</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="15" to="50" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="1996"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b45">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Projector augmented-wave method</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">P</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">E</forename>
                  <surname>Blochl</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="17953" to="17979" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="1994"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b46">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">From ultrasoft pseudopotentials to the projector augmented-wave method</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">G</forename>
                  <surname>Kresse</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">D</forename>
                  <surname>Joubert</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Phys. Rev. B</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="1758" to="1775" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="1999"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct xml:id="b47">
            <analytic>
              <title level="a" type="main">Generalized gradient approximation made simple</title>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">J</forename>
                  <forename type="middle">P</forename>
                  <surname>Perdew</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">K</forename>
                  <surname>Burke</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
              <author>
                <persName>
                  <forename type="first">M</forename>
                  <surname>Ernzerhof</surname>
                </persName>
              </author>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
                <biblScope from="3865" to="3868" unit="page"/>
                <date type="published" when="1996"/>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
